<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-los-angeles-times-bombing</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	      <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88084272/1910-10-01/ed-1/?sp=1</id>
	      <rel>1</rel>
	      <text>LOS ANGELES TIMES PLANT
WRECKED BY EXPLOSION
AND TWENTY ARE KILLED
Disaster Occurs At 1 Oclock
In The Morning While Employees
Are At Work In The Building And Many Are 
Caught In the Debris and Crushed To Death
Or Burned in the Fire Which
Follows the Explosion.
Property Loss Half a Million Dollars
Gen. Harrison 'Gray Otis Principal Owner of Paper, Was in El Paso Friday The
Oauseof the Explosion Not Definitely Determined, But -Management
of the Paper Attributes It to the Troubles It Has Had With
Labor Organizations Building and Plant Reported
Completely "recked.
Los Angeles, Calif., Oct. 1. The
building and plant of the Lod Angeles
Times, one of the best knewn news
papers in the southwest, of which "Gen.
Harrison Gray Otis is editor, and princi
pal owner, was completely destroyed
by an explosion and tire shortly after
1 o'clock this morning, resulting in the
death of upward of 20 of its employes
and the financial loss of nearly
500.000.
The management lays the blame for
the explosion to labor unions, with
which the paper has long been en
gaged in bitter warfare.
It is charged that unidentified par-,
ties set off the charge of dynamite in
a blind alley which ran into the center
of the building, wrecking the interior
and setting it afire from roof to base
ment. J
The force of the explosion was ter-
rific. It was heard for miles, and all
windows in the vicinity of the Times"
building, on First street and Broad
way, were shattered. Between 50 and
70" employes were in the structure at
the time, 'and juntil the list can be'
checked, it will be impossible to giv.e
jjo. accurate list of casualties.
TSeads of Paper Have Narrow Escapes.
The heaas of the paper, including
assistant general manager Harry
Chandler, had narrow escapes from
death. The building was equipped with
gas fittings and the force of the ex
plosion, tearing these pipes to pieces,
released gas, which ignited in every
part of the building.
No other cause but that of a dyna
mite explosion is advanced by wit
nesses, except in the case of the West
em Union telegraph operator, "William
Firman, who stated that he detected
an odor of gas throughout the building
early in the night and called atten
tion to it.
A few minutes after the explosion
the police arrested a man named Harry
Pluke, who was making his way
through the Broadway tunnel. Another
man named William Irwin was arrest
ed later, but the police are without
clews.
Wesley Reeves, secretary to manager
Chandler, is among the missing, and it
is believed he lost his life.
Chandler Makes Statement.
"You can say for me," said Mr.
Chandler, "there is no doubt that this
terrible outrage can be laid at the
door of the labor unions. They have
destrojed the building and killed a
number of our men, but they can't kill
the Times. There is no doubt but that
the explosion was caused by a charge
of dynamue placed apparently in a
little blind alley in the center of the
building. It is true the building was
equipped with gas, but no gas explos
ion could have caused it. For vear3 5
we have been receiving threatening
letters from people who said the paper
ought to be blown up."
The Times was issued today from the
Herald plant and from an auxiliary
plant of the Times in another part of
the city. Manager Chandler said that
two years ago the Times had establish
ed aft auxiliary plant, equipping it
with a press and 12 linotype machines
with the expectation of the present
plant some day being destroyed.
Many Are Misnlnir.
The' dead and missing come princi
pally from the composing room, which
was directly above the spot where the
explosion took place. A number of
printers and linotypers are missing
and believed to be buried in the still
burning debris in the basement of the
building.
.In the local room, all the editors and
reporters had gone home, except two
or three men. Assistant city editor
Harvey Elder was still on duty when
the explosion came. When the flames
shot up through all parts Aof the build
ing, Elder -was badly stunned, but at
tempted to escape. He ran to the win
dows opening on Broadway, but there
was no fire escape thep, and he was
hemmed in by the flames. He jumped.
P'iremen below held a net, but he
missed it and struck the pavement,
dying soon afterwards.
Night editor Taggart was at work
in the composing room. He leaped
through a window and made his way
across the roofs of adjoining buildings
safely. The entire force of telegraph
editors and operators -was at work, ex
cept telegraph editor R. N. Whitney.
Harry C. Crane; assistant editor, was
seen attempting to make his way out
of the building, but has not been found
among the survivors. Several men
wore seen to come to upper windows a
few moments after the fire brake out,
and were heard to cry for help. Nets
were stretched and many jumped to
Employes Are At,
Many' Are Caught In the
Crushed To
in the Fire
4-
5 THE KNOWN DEAD.
Los Aageles, CaL, Oct. 1,
5 The known dead as a result of
the wrecking of the Los An
geles Times building early this
morning,' are;
Haryey C. Elder, assistant
city editor, leaped from third
story- window,- died in the hos--
pital. f
Charles E. Lovelace country
news editor, leaped from third 4
story window and died in the
hospital.
J. .Wesley Reaves, secretary' f
to assistant general manager
Chandler. It is believed his body 4
a is in the ruins. 4
1I- -L. Jaw-verr- telegraph oper-a -Hh
'41 ator, aged 34,, married, two chil-
v w ca. x
8 Harry L. $rane, assistant tele-
graph editor, aged 38, married,
one child.
f Injured and Missing.
5 Among the injured taken to
the hospital are:
4" S. W. Gray, bill foreman of
the composing room, severe
bruises; Randolph Rossi, linb
typer, jumped from second floor,
severe.
The following are included in
the- missing:
Jr C. Galligher, linotype oper
ator, married, five children;
W. G. Tunstall, linotype oper
ator, married; Fre.d Llewellyn,
linotype operator, married;
John Howard, printer, married,
one child; Grant Moore, machin
ist, mairried, three children; Ed- "S"
ward Wasson, printer, married; 4"
Elmer Frink, linotype operator,
married; Eugene Carres, lino-
type operator, married, one
child; Done E. Johnson, linotype
5 operator, married;, Ernest Jor-
dan, linotype operator, married,
one child; Frank Underwood,
printer, married, one child; Carl 4
Sallada, linotype operator;
4 Charles Gulllveri compositor, 4"
married. 41
4" 444'44 4'4' 4'
safety. Others were seen to fall hack
into the flames.
One Hundred and Fifteen in Building.
Foreman Grayblll, of the composing
room, estimated toda3' that there -were
115 men In the building. He believes
12 of his men -were killed and the fa
talities in other departments about the
same number. About 15 men were in
the stereotyping department, but. he
thinks all of these escaped. Eight
women in the proofreading room, on
the third floor, also escaped.
Says It Was Second Attempt.
Assistant manager chandler is au
thority for the statement that an at
tempt to blolv up the Times plant was
made before' the explosion which de
stroyed the main office. He said one
of his men reported shortly before 1
o'clock this morning that two men
were seen by a special officer placing
a ladder at the rear of the branch
building and were climbing onto the
roof. The officer says that, he fired at
them twice and the men fled. Chief
of Police Galloway said it seemed cer
tain that the Times building was
wrecked by dynamite.
Call Off Labor Parade.
Mayor Alexander, the city council,
the city attorney, the chief of riollce
and other municipal officials met with
the officials of various local unions
today and mutually agreed, to call oft
the union labor parade which was to
have been held Monday. The parade
was arranged as a protest against the
anti-pleketing ordinance. It was
agreed that the parade during the
present excitement would be unwise.
Persons who were first on the scene
state that there were three distinct ex
plosions. The first seemed to be tho
heaviest and occurred under the second
floor, which is used as a composing
room.
The Wrecked Building.
The building occupied by he Times
was located on the southeast corner of
Broadway and First street, fronting
about 30 feet on First street and ex
tending 75 or 100 feet along Broadway.
The main building was- of rick, nrev
stories in v height and back( of this
jvas a brick annex, two stories and
basement. The editorial department
was on the third floor of the main build
ing. The business offices were on the
ground flo"br. The annex contained
presses, linotypes, big job printing
In the Mornin
Work Ire ,the
Death Or
Which
plant and the Times school for training
linotype operators. The Times em
ployed non-union printers and main
tained a large battery of linotypes for
teaching and training operators in the
use of those machines.
Long Opposed Unions.
For 20 years the Times has been at
war with labor unions, starting with a
strike of the members of the typograph
ical union employed on the paper. Gen.
Otis is on his way back from Mexico
City and Is expected here today. Po
lice had fire lines stretched around the
scene soon after the fire broke out and
reserves were patroling the district
armed with riot clubs, but the half clad
crowd which silently watched the
flames from behind the fire lines- was
orderly" 'anSPuotf 'an arrest was made
from the crowd.
PRESIDENT LYNCH RESENTS
f CHARGE AGAINST UNIQNS
Indianapolis, Ind., Oct. 1. "The Los
Angeles Times for many years has been
a bitter, unrelenting and unreasoning
enemy of trades unionism, and it is
characteristic of the Times manage
ment that, without waiting to investi
gate it should charge the disaster to
the trades unions," said president
James M. Lynch, of the International
Typographical union, today.
"The typographical union resents
and refutes this charge," said Mr.
Lynch. "We have always fought fair.
The International Typographical union
Is not a law breaking, dynamiting In
stitution. Its record of more than 60
years' existence Is an honorable one.
No one regrets the Times catastrophe
more than I do. On the other hand, we
are determined to protect ourselves
against the opportunity embraced by
Gen. Otis and his subordinates to at
tempt to fasten the explosion on the
trades unions."
President! Lynch said he had wired
his Los Angeles representative to take
necessary measures to protect fthe In
ternational Typographical union and
the local union from the charge of com
plicity, "as the press reports convince
us the explosion was caused by faulty
gas mains and was due entirely to the
unsanitary condition of the Times
plant."
GOMPERS SAYS HE DOESN'T
THINK UNION MEN DID IT
St. Louis, Mo., "Oct. 1. Samuel Gom
pers, president of the American Federa
tion of Labor said today he did not be
lieve union labor members were in any
way responsible for the explosrti and
fire which destroyed the building of the
Los Angeles Times.
"The position of tne Times toward
union labor wag well known," said Mr.
Gompers, "but nothing has happened
recently to make the feeling of the
unlon men against the paper more acute.
I regret the loss of lives, and destruc
tion of property, but see no reason for
thinking that union members had any
thing to do with it"
FIND BOMB UNDER MAN'S
HOUSE, SAY THE POLICE
Los Angeles, Cal.,
Oct.
-F. J.
Zeechandelaar, secretary of the Mer
chants' and Manufacturers' association
telephoned the police this morning he
had found a charge of dynamite under
his house. Police were sent to investi
gate and found a bomb.
GEN. OTIS, OWNER OF THE
TIMES, IN EL PASO FRIDAY
Gen. Harrison Gray Otis, managing
editor of the Los Angeles Times, was
in El Paso Friday on his way home
from Mexico City, where he attended
the centennial celebration as a delegate
from California. Gen. Otis left on tne
and was due to arrive in Los Angeles
Saturday afternoon at
4 oclock.
Two El Paso men, it Is said, were on
the Los Angeles Times at the time of
the explosion. Al D. Greene, formerly
news editor of the old El Paso Evening
News, and Eddie Kelley, a printer em
ployed, it is said, on the Times, was also
formerly employed in the El Paso print
ing offices.
Henry Aguirre, a pressman, "who has
been employed on El Paso papers was.
it is said, working in the pressroom of
the Los Angeles Times until two weeks
ago when he returned to El Paso for a
visit and was to nave returned in timu
to resume work Friday but decided to
stay here and work on one of the local
papers.
       </text>
      </result>
      <result>
	      <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86072041/1910-10-01/ed-1/?sp=1</id>
	      <rel>1</rel>
	      <text>DYNAMITE LOS ANGELES "TIMES"
Many Employes Killed and Los Angeles Times Build
ing a Total Loss With Property Damage to Amount
of Half a Million—Loss is Accredited to Labor Unions
With Which it Had Waged an Unceasing Warfare.
Los Angeles, CaL, Oct. I.—The building and plain of
the Los Angeles Times, one of the best known newspa
pers of the southwest, of which General Harrison Gray
Otis is editor and principal owner, was eompeltely de
stroyed by an explosion and tire shortly after 1 oYlock
this morning, resulting in the death of upwards of twen
ty employes and a financial loss of nearly half a million
dollars. The management of the paper lays the blame
of the explosion on the labor unions, with which organ
izations the paper lias long been engaged in a bitter
warfare.
It is charged that unknown par-1
ties set off a heavy charge of dvna-1
mite in a blind alley which ran into j
the center of the building, complete
ly wrecking the interior and setting
it on fire from roof to basement. The
force of the explosion was terrific
and was heard for miles. All the
windows in the vicinity of the Times
building at First and Broadway were
shattered. Between 50 and 75 em-!
ployes were Mi the building at the
time of the explosion, and until the
i
whole list of employes of the paper
can be checked over it will not be i
known how many lives were lost.
The responsible heads of the pa- 1
per, including Assistant General
Manager Harry Chandler, had nar
row escapes from death, many of
them having left the building a
short time before the explosion.
The fire spread throughout the I
building with amazing rapidity, and
in the course of but a few seconds j
the flames were bursting from every j
window and door in the building,
shooting high above the roof.
Xo Clue to Perpetrators.
The building was equipped with
gasfittings and the force of the ex
plosion tearing *these pipes into bits
released the gas, which was instant
ly ignited in every part of the build
ing.
There is no other cause than dy
namite, is the evidence of witnesses,
except in the one case of the West
ern Union telegraph operator, Wm.
Firmin, who stated that he detected
the odor of gas throughout the
building early in the night and had
called the attention of others to it.
A few minutes after the explosion
the police arrested a man named
Harry Lake, who was making his
way through the Broadway tunnel a
few blocks distant. He was locked
up on suspicion. Another man
named William Irwin was arrested
and afterward taken to the station.
The police are without clues, how
ever.
Assistant General Manager Chand
ler narrowly escaped with his life.
His office was on the ground floor
and he left a few minutes before the
explosion. He is accustomed to re
main in his office until late in the
morning but last night his wife came
for him and he went home earlier
than usual. His secretary, I. T.
Westley Reaves, remained in the of
fice and is among the missing.
Says Ijabor Unions Responsible.
Speaking of the explosion. Mr.
Chandler said: "You can say for
me that there is no doubt that this
terrible outrage can be laid to the
doors of the labor unions. They have
destroyed the building and plant and
have killed a number of our men.
We do not know how many, but they
cannot kill the Times. There is no
doubt but that the explosion was
caused by a charge of dynamite. No
other agency could have caused it.
There was no oil in the building, we
had no boilers to explode, there was
no gasoline in the place excepting a
small can or two in the composing
room. It is true the building was
equipped with gas, but no explosion
of gas could have caused it. It was
evidently aimed to destroy the plant,
and kill as many as possible of the
employes. For years we have been
receiving threatening letters from
people who said that the paper ought
to be blown up. 1 have not received
any such letters lately, although I
have had several telephone calls
within the past few weeks, threaten
ing us with destruction.''
Had Auxiliary Plant.
Two years ago. in anticipation of
just such a thing as has occurred
this morning, the Times established
an auxiliary plant, equipped with
linotypes and presses. The Times
was issued today from the plant of
the Morning Herald and the Times
auxiliary plant.
General Otis was absent from the
city when the newspaper was de
stroyed this morning. He is on his
Established July 4,190f
5c PER COPY
I way back to Los Angeles from The
!City of Mexico, where he went some
weeks ago as a representative of the
United States government by ap
pointment from President Taft to the
celebration of the Mexican centen
nial. General Otis is due to arrive
in Los Angeles late this afternoon.
The building in which the Times
was housed was stone and brick. The
part four stories high is of stone,
built in ISS7. The six stories of
brick were added later.
Many From Composing Hoom Ieatl.
The dead and missing come prin
cipally from the composing room,
which was directly above where the
explosion occurred. A number of
primers and linotype operators are
missing and it is believed are buried
in the still burning ruins and debris.
All but three or four of the editorial
staff had gone home but the entire
force of telegraph editors and tele
graph operators was at work, with
the exception of one man, who had
just left the building. Those in thp
building made their way to the win
dows wherever possible, and some
jumped to the roofs of the adjoining
buildings. Many jumped to the
street, but some who had climbed
into the windows were seen to fall
back into the flames. Owing to the
wrecked condition of the building
many are believed to have been un
able to reach the windows or other
exits.
Called Off Labor Parade.
Mayor Alexander, the city council, j
chief of police and other municipal
officials met today with representa
tives of tbe labor unions. It was re
solved to call off the proposed union
labor parade Monday in protest
against the anti-picketing ordinance
and other alleged anti-union labor
'conditions exisiting in the city. It
j was agreed that such assemblage in
tbe midst of the present excitement
was unwise.
The city council voted a $25,000
•fund to be used to run down the
i perpetrators of the alleged dynamit
ing of the Los Angeles Times. The
j $25,000 was made available as a re
j ward for the capture of the culprit
jor culprits.
Pressmen Kscaped.
The men in the pressroom, which
j was in the basement, all escaped. It
'is estimated that 125 men were in the
building at the time of the explosion.
Two Watchmen Kmployed.
The Times employed two night
i watchmen but they saw no one about
the building to arouse their sus
picions. One of the watchmen was
jv, B. Glasier. He was not found
land it is believed he perished.
Tried to Blow Up Auxiliary Plant.
Manager Chandler is authority for
the statement that a similar attempt
was made to blow up the Times' aux
iliary plant last night. One of the
employes saw two men trying to
climb to the roof. He fired two shots
at them. The men fled. He inter
prets this second attemps as further
proof of a carefully planned effort
made last night to destroy both the
Times main and branch office.
Would Blow Up Zeehandelaar.
Additional excitement was dis
covered in an infernal machine un
der the residence of Secretary F. J.
Zeehandelaar of the Merchants and
Manufacturers' association, who has
been active in conjunction with the
Los Angeles Times in opposition to
labor unions. The machine was dis
covered by Special Officer Hendrick
son. who. under instructions from
the chief of police, placed the ma-
chine, which was of clockwork pat
tern, in an isolated place. No arrGats
have been made. The deadly char
acter of the bomb was established
by the police and detectives. It con
sisted of 15 sticks of dynamite at
tached to a fuse with clockwork at-
tachment.
An attempt was made this after
noon to dynamite the home of Gen
eral Otis, but nod-image was done.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88085620/1910-10-21/ed-1/?sp=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>LOS ANGELES DISASTER
REVIEWED BY GENE DEBS
In Caustic Sentences Labor Leader Shows Utter Fal
lacy of Charge Made by Otis—The Animus Behind
the Attack Upon Organized Labor Fully Exposed
Tho blowing up of the Los Angeles
Times and the snuffing out of twentj
human lives is another of the atrocious
crimes committed in the heat mid pas
sion of the class war. Who committed
that crime 1 Harrison Cray Otis, pro
prielor of the 'l imes, and the capitalist
PKBB of the Pacific Coast in general,
charge it directly and specifically up
explosion whs followed by the charge
thai union labor was guilty of the crime
as swiftly as the capitalist press could
telegraph the indictment to the coun
try.
It appears well settled in Mr. Otis'
statement and the 'limes account that
the Times building was blown up by
dynamite, and equally well settled that
the crime was committed by labor
unionists. As one who knows the Los
Angeles Times by personal experience
with that vicious, lying and criminal
sheet I want to express it as my de
liberate opinion that the Times and its
crowd of union haters are themselves
the instigators, if not the actual per
petrators of that crime and the mur
ders of the twenty human beings who
perished ns its victims.
First of all, let me relate my own
experience with General Harrison Otis
nnd the Los Angeles Times. At the
time of the railroad strike in 1894, the
Los Angeles Times lied about me out
rageously, charged me with every con
ceivable crime, editorially stated that 1
deserved the gallows and did all in its
power to send me there. Shortly nfter
the strike I went to Los Angeles to
give a public address. The following
morning the Times had a column of
editorial abuse and vilification the like
of which has randy appeared in public
print, but not a word of my address.
I was charged with arson, conspiracy,
treason. murder, and assassination.
There were in this villlanous article
thirteen deliberate, clear-cut. mnde-to
order, montsrous lies. 1 nt once con
cluded to return to Los Angeles nfter
filling my immediate engagements nnd
make answer to this outrageous indict
ment; and here let me ssy that any
man who would make such false and
fiendish charges against another to glut
his insane hatred of organized labor
would commit any other crime to serve
the same base end.
A few days later I returned to Los
Angeles to find the old Hazard's pa
vilion packed to the doors, every inch
of stnnding room occupied nnd thou
sands turned away, to hear my answer
to Otis and the Times. It so happened
that I had in my grip the documentary
evidence, including government reports,
to prove my innocence of the most
vicious of these charges. In one hand
I held up the Los Angeles -Times and
in the other the positive proof of its
criminal mendacity. I went through
the thirteen charges seriatim and liter
ally tore them to tatters. I had not
proceeded far »nt>\ some one in the
audience shouted, "Otis is In the house,"
and this proved to be true. I at on'-e
challenged General Otis to come for
ward nnd face me, whom he had so out
rage lonely maligned, before his own
people. It is needless to sny that, al
though the crowd yelled "Otis, Otis,
Otis," he did not dare to come and he
would gladly have disappeared if the
packed nnd Jammed condition of tha
hall had not barred his escape.
But from that day to this, although
their monstrous lies have long since
found them out, General Otis and his
keproUS sheet have never uttered one
word of retraction, and it is not their
fault that I was not lynched or hanged
for crimes of which 1 was as innocent
ns are the union men of Los Angeles
upon Whom General Otis is now seeking
to fasten his atroeioias calumnies as
he did upon me and my fellow-union
ists fifteen yenrs ago.
Now let us examine some of the facts
in regard to the blowing up of the
Times and some of the circumstantial
evidence, nnd let us see if it is not im
possible to escape at least the inference,
if not the positive conclusion, that Otis
and his gang are themselves the con
spirators and criminals.
The theory that he who is benefited
by a crime is most apt to have a hand
in its commission is peculiarly appli
cable to this case. Financially and
morally Otis and the Times have every
thing to gain as certainly as organized
labor ban everything to lose in bearing
the crushing odium of the crime. 1/ot
it Ik- remembered that General Otis was
perfectly certain that the outrage, si
most before it was committed, was the
dnstardly act of union laW. He per
sonnlly was at a safe distance, and all
th* vie tims were wage slaves, and what
do Otis and his crowd of exploiting
plutocrats care sbottt the lives of
slaves* Vow for a few of these facts:
First, The class war on the Pacific
Coast had reached it* acntest stage and
EVERETT. WASHINGTON. FRIDAY. OCTOBER 21, 1910.
was rapidly approaching a grave crisis
at the time of the explosion. It was in
striking analogy to the blowing up of
the Independence platform in the class
war in Colorado five years ago, nnd we
now know beyond the shadow of a
doubt what side committed thai re
volting crime and what was its ob
ject.
Second. The tide of organised labor
in California was steadily rising, the
Socialist campaign was in full swing,
and there was to be a culminating
'demonstration of the united labor forces
[at Los Angeles but a few days after
t'ho Times was blown up. This dem
onstration was promptly called off by
'the leaders of the unions, a grievous
blunder on their pnrt, which places
them in a defensive nnd apologetic at
titude utterly unwarranted by the cir
cumstances of the situation. Instend
of pleading not guilty to the criminal
charge preferred against the workers,
without a scintilla of proof they should
have immediately accused Otis nnd his
gang of union-haters nnd called upon
them to prove that their own hands
were not red with the crime.
Third, Tho l\os Angeles Times is the
most venomous foe of organized labor
in the United States nnd its own record
prove* that there is no crime too nl>
horrent for it to commit to wreck its
vengeance on the labor movement.
Fourth, The statement is made by the
Times itself and confirmed by press
dispatches from Chicago that General
Otis, "having antlcipatd just such an
eventuality." hnd a duplicate printing
plant and n duplicate working force in
reserve, all in readiness to leap into the
breach nnd rescue the paper when the
expected bomb exploded. This admis
sion proves too much. It is fatal to
Otis and file Times. What cause had
Otis to anticipate the explosion nn.l
prepare for it? Suppose a labor union
ist had made such an admission, or
even intimated that he knew the ex
plosition would occur, would he not
promptly be arrested on suspicion nnd
lodged in jail?
Yes. we are only too ready to be
lieve that Otis and his pals expected
the explosion and were entirely pre
pared for it when it came.
Fifth, The united league of newspa
pers which embraces a chain of daily
papers scattered over the country, and
friendly in their attitude towards or
ganized labor, recently sent a special cor
respondent to California to investigate
conditions growing out of the war be
tween lalior and capital on the Pacific
Coast, nnd his series of articles is now
running in those papers. These articles
describe a situation and a desperation
on the part of the capitalists that has
a fitting climax in the blowing up of
the Times, as the same war had in the
blowing up of the Independence plat
form in Colorado.
In the second article of this series-—
and let it be remembered that these are
capitalist papers and not Inlaw papers
the capitalists composing the manu
facturers' association are described as
in a state bordering on frenzy in their
determination to utterly annihilate "at
any cost and at all hazards" organized
labor on the Pacific Const. The chnir
innn is personally quoted as saying to
the correspondent representing these
capitalist newspapers: WK WILL
NEVER CEASK UNTIL THE LAST
VESTIGE OF UNION LABOR HAS
BEEN WIPED OFF THE PACIFIC
COAST."
This vehement and bloodthirsty de
claration was made only a short time
before the Times was blown up nnd the
united workers, a few days later, were
to have their mnminoth demonstration.
Sixth, The discovery of the I ib
is the one fareinl feature of this grue
some tragedy, which every human being
not utterly void of feeling must de
plore with all his heart. To prove that
it was the fiendish plot of unionists,
other bombs, accessories to the crime,
and |Kinting to the identity of its per
petrators, must Ik- located and un
earthed. Of course it was known in
stantaneously where to look for the
bosahs, and of course they were sll
found according to specifications. In
each case they were located at the pal
ntial homes of the proprietors and man
SMS of the 'limes and the manufactur
ers' association. BUT IN NO CASE DID
ONE OF THESE BOMBS EXPLODE.
The bomb that did explode blew up
the wage slaves of the Times only; the
bombs that did not explode did not
blow up any of the aristocratic owners
and managers. there is a peculiar
bomb consciousness in evidence here
flint clearly draws the line between
capitalists and wuge workers.
In Chicago following the Haymarket
riot a regular crop of bombs was har
vested in plutocratic reservations until
finally the thing was overworked by
(Continued on Page Four.)
of Organized Labor
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn99063957/1910-10-28/ed-1/?sp=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>EXPLOSION CAUSED BY GAS SAYS
LABOR FEDERATION COMMITTEE
EFFECTS PRODUCED SHOW
IT WAS NOT DYNAMITE THAT
WRECKED TIMES BUILDING
San Francisco, Oct. 28. That the
Los Angeles Times was destroyed as
a result of the explosion of gas", and
not by dynamite, Is the finding of the
committee of the executive council
of the California State Federation of
Labor, which for four weeks haa been
working on the investigation of the
catastrophe. The report has Just been
submitted to the federation.
The report is prefaced with a de
tailed account of the committee's re
ception by Mayor Alexander, of Los
Angeles, when It called upon him and
informed him that it desired to co
operate with the citizens' committee
appointed by the city council to in
vestigate the disaster. The mayor
refused to grant the request. The
committee then determined on an in
vestigation of its own. After, some
parley the committee secured permis
sion to pass the police lines and
viewed the wreckage' from the prop
erty adjoining the Times building.
Salem's
IS OUT THIS WEEK
With the biggest bargains we ever offered in up-to-date, seasonable merchandise. Qual
ity, Style and Low Prices are what keep us growing. Come here for the best val
ues for your money.
IK.- a j I f I
.Dress Goods and Silks
Right thinking is what makes the world grow, and right buying la what makes the business grow. Come
to our store and let us demonstrate to you these truthful aaylngs. Other merchants wonder bow It Is the
Chicago Store could grow so fast. It Is all in understanding the business. In DRESS GOODS AND SILKS
we can give you the best values In Salem.
THE GREATER
Smelled the Gas All Day Before
At this time even the city employes
had been ordered oft of the property
by the Times owners, the report says.
The report then recites the princi
pal facts of the explosien, and the
subsequent events, referring to the
fact that the Time sitself, in the issue
on the morning of the explosion, and
before there was any time for inves
tigation, it alleges, charged that the
explosion was caused by the enemies
of "Industrial freemdom." The re
port refers to articles printed in sub
sequent Issues of the Times charging
union labor with responsibility for the
catastrophe.
"Inasmuch as there many persons
who are not acquainted with Gener
al Harrison Gray Otis and his news
paper," the report continues, "and
who, therefore, naturally would sup
pose that there exists evidence to sup
port such assertions, it would seem
Important to shed some light on the
matter?'
The report then .reviewed General
Otis' fight against unionism in Los
Angeles, saying, among other things,
that "on the subject of Industrial
freedom it is no exaggeration to say
that General Otis is Insane."
The report further says the dream
of the general's life haa been to ex
terminate unionism la Los Angeles.
"Trumptelng abroad the report
that unionists were plotting to d6 htm
violence, Otis made his editorial
rooms an arsenal," the report says.
It then refers to the bitter fight made
by the Times against the unions dur
ing the recent strike of the metal
and brewery workers in Los Angeles,
and continues:'
"Such was the situation Just pre
vious to the blowing up of the Times.
It has not been determined that the
building was destroyed by dynamite.
The only two points which possibly
(Continued on Page 4.)
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1911-04-23/ed-1/?sp=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>LABOR LEADERS
BRAND DYNAMITE
ARREST AS PLOT
McNamara, National Secretary of Iron
workers, Being Rushed to Los Angeles
By Secret Route.
DETECTIVE BURNS FAILS
IN RAIDS FOR EVIDENCE
Detectives operating under orders from William J. Burns, are today
secretly spiriting to Los Angeles, John J. McNamara, of the International
Structural Iron Workers, there to try him for dynamiting and murder.
President Samuel Gompers and Secretary Frank Morrison, of the
American Federation of Labor, in Washington, President James M. Lynch,
of the Typographical Union, in Indianapolis, and many other great leaders
of labor, today declare that this is an attack on organized labor of the
country, not merely on McNamara.
In Indianapolis, Detective Burns failed in one hunt for evidence to
prove McNamara is the leader of dynamiters. Early this morning Burns
had the safe at the union headquarters blown open, but did not find any
thing to incriminate McNamara.
From Los Angeles it Is reported that another labor leader, noted on
the Pacific coast, will be under arrest before night, on the charge of
being the Pacific manager of what the Burns men term the "dynamiting
conspiracy."
This afternoon the attorney for the Structural Iron Workers in In
dianapolis made the charge that the private papers of the international
association were seized by Detective Burns and turned over bodily to
the Erectors' Association, the manufacturers' organization, which Is
financing Detective Burns In this fight The papers have been ordered
returned.
In Chicago it Is understood that
Manlgal, arrested as the ag
of Secretary McNamara, are still being
concealed there by officer' j who fear to 
start them on the journey for Los Angeles.
Labor Leaders Brand
Arrest of McNamara
As "Infamous Outrage"
Applying tho brand of "infamous out
rage" to the arrest in indlanapolU last
night of John J. McNamara, interna
tional secretary of the Bridge and Struc
tural Iron Workers of America, official.?
of the American Federation of Labor
today declared that the charge made
against McNamara of complicity in the
dynamiting of the Los Angeles Times
office Is nothing more than another at
tempt of capitalists to discredit organ
ized labor In the eyes of the world.
That dynamite was "planted" In the
barn near Indianapolis and hidden in
the storerooms of the Iron Workers'
Union building by opponents of unions,
anxious to make evidence against them.
Is the belief of such officers as Presi
dent Samuel Gompers and Secretary
Frank Morrison of the American Fede
ration of Labor. The same belief Is held
by William J. Spencer, secretary of the
building trades department of the
American Federation of Labor and a
personal friend of the accused official.
"Legalized Kidnaping."
Forceful words were used by the
American Federation officials in their
endeavor to express their contempt for
tho Injustice they believe has been done
Secretary McNamara in spiriting him
away from Indianapolis without, grant
ing him legal representation, or even
communication with his friends.
"How long are the American people
going to stand for legalized kidnap
ing?" With this query Samuel Gompers.
president of the American Federation
of Labor, today declares his belief in
the innocence of union steel worker,
arrested at Indianapolis for alleged
complicity in dynamiting outrages.
Angrily and Indignantly, President
Gompers charges the arrest to en
emies of organized labor, a plot to
destroy labor unions by huge money
Interests. He characterizes the sum
mary removal of McNamara from In
dianapolis to California as "high
handed legal kidnaping."
"McNamara's extradition is a gross
ly outrageous piece of legalized kid
naping," 6aid President Gompers this
morning at his home, 2122 First street
northwest.
In Class With Haywood Case.
"Nothing except the Haywood, Moy
er, and Pettlbone case equals It in the
besmirched history of attacks upon
organized labor," said President Gom
pers. "McNamara was spirited away with
out giving him the slightest chance
to gltfe prima facie, evidence of his
Innocence taken from hi3 own home
and State without aid of friends or
attorneys," President Gompers con
tinued with passion.
Declaring the arrest of the union
men "smacks of theatricals," Presi
dent Gompers said.
"The staga was all set, the properties
arranged carefully and then up goe3
the curtain, with a blare of trumpets,
upon the first act .of a tragedy contem
plating the assasination of organized
labor.
"Every since the Los Angeles Times
tragedy the 'interests' have been trying
to fasten guilt upon organized labor. It
might just as welt be McNamara as
another. The whole affair smacks of
well laid pre-arrangement.
"The 'interests' of corporate wealth
are alwavs trvlne to crush the organ
ized labor movement and they use the
(Continued on Sixth page.)
Detectives Hurrying
McNamara to Coast
City By Secret Route
IN'HIANAPOUS. Abril 23--CompIetel
baffled by Detective W. J. Euros. In
their rtorts to stop the spiriting away
to Los Angele of John J. McNamara to
l)f tried there for the Times dynamiting,
a score of international labor leadens
here todav aio wildly indignant and are
preparing appeals to the country.
Burns answers by saying this noon
"There Is more dynamite In Indianap
olis, and I am going to And it."
Meanwhile Burns has McNamara -well
on his way to Los Ajigeles, though no
one has yet found lust how far. The
only vestige of information obtained so
far bv McNamara's friends has been
that the journev to Chicago, whether
completed yd or not. Is bv automobile,
evidently so that the route cannot be
foreseen and legal obstacles made.
On one point the labor leaders arc
Jubilant. All last night and up to the
parly hours of this morning the officers
of the International Structural Iron
Workers fought the efforts of Detective
Burns to open the safe of the organi
zation, which was used by McNamara
as secretary-treasurer. But in spite of
their opposition Bums finally had thi
safe blown open early this morning, only
to find not the sllchtest bit of evidence
against the accused. Bums himself ad
mitted the failure, this morning.
Pacific Coast Leader Sought
From Los Angeles has come the well
accredited report that a warrant has
been issued for still another noted labor
leader, this one a Pacific coast leader,
charging htm with being the Pacific
coast manager of what the Burns men
call the dynamite conspiracy. This man
Is expected to bo under arrest before
night.
It is known to the labor leaders here
that the other two men who are under
arrest In connection with the affair
James W. McNamara, of Cincinnati,
brother of Secretary McNamara. alias
J. B. Bryce, and Ortle E. McManlgal. of
Chicago already are on their long trip
to Los Angeles, in the custody of Los
Angeles police.
In spite of the failure of Burns to find
any evidence In the safe at headquar
ters, and in spite of the failure of two
of his men, Shlnn and Dugan. to find
anything Incriminating In a search of
McNamara's room, so far as can be
learned, the whole Burns force Is Jubi
lant today over the two discoveries of
dynamite, one in the basement store
room of the iron workers' building, and
the other in the barn In the outskirts
of the city, owned by T H. Jones.
They point out that the evidence of
Jones is the strongest of all yet brought
out. He is an Iron worker himself, and
told his story reluctantly. It Is to the
effect that he rented his barn In Janu
ary to McNamara for J23 a month and
had frequently seen McNamara and
others going and coming to the barn
with heavy suit cases.
Fight to Get At Safe.
The blowing of the safe of the Inter
national Structural Iron Workers early
this morning was accomplished only
after many difficulties. When the de
tectives went to the union headauarters
in the American Central Life Building
last night. President Ryan, of tho Inter
national Union, was ready for them,
and was prepared to fight.
Tho detectives presented a search
warrant, and demanded access to the
safe of the union. President Ryan
refused, and the detectives then pre
pared to go ahead. A lawyer for the
ui.ion then Interfared. and his op
position was so vigorous and appar
ently sound that the Burns men final
ly went back to Judge Collins and
obtained another search warrant, spe
cifically giving them the right to
search the safe.
Oliver W. Irensee. an expert lock
smith, first tried to work the com
bination, but some time after midnight
It was decided that this would not
(Continued on Seventh Page.)
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85066387/1911-04-24/ed-1/?sp=2</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>CONGRESS IS ASKED
TO PROBE ARRESTS
IN DYNAMITE CASES
Berger Introduces Resolution and Doubje-
Barreled Investigation May Follow If
"Third Degree" Charges Are Pressed.
GOMPERS AND SPENCER LEAVE
CITY ON SOME SECRET MISSION
A double-barreled Investigation by Congress is the latest promised
development in the arrest of John J. McNamara, James W. McNamara,
and Ortie McManigal, the three men now being hurried to Los Angeles
to face charges of dynamiting and murder.
Representative Berger, the Socialist member of the House, today
introduced his resolution demanding a Federal Investigation of the
methods used in removing John J. McXamara from Indianapolis, and
the securing of an alleged confession from Ortie McManigal by "third
degree" methods.
A representative of the Senate Third Degree Committee held a
long conference with Samuel Gompers yesterday afternoon, and it Is
likely that a meeting of this committee will be called in the near future.
John E. Wilkie, chief of the United States Secret Service, and Stanley
Finch, head of the Bureau of Investigation of the Department of Justice,
today denied that their Secret Service men had at any time assisted
Burns' detectives in the investigation of the dynamite outrages.
President Gompers, of the Federation of Labor, and William J.
Spencer, secretary of the building trades department of the Federation,
left the city today on a secret mission.
The McNamara brothers and Ortie McManigal passed through Den
ver today on their way to Los Angeles.
District Attorney Fredericks, of Los Angeles, announces that the
arrested men will be prosecuted as individuals, and no attempt will be
made to fasten the crime on organized labor.
Berger Resolution
Calls Upon Congress
Fpr An Investigation
Throvtl. -h resolution, which he in
troduced in the House of Representa
tives, this afternoon. Representative
Victor Berger of Wisconsin has de
manded a Federal investigation of tho
treatment received by the two McNa
mara? and McManigal since their arrest
on charges of complicity In the wreck
ing of The Times ofrtce at Los Angeles.
Tho demand Is based on the claim that
there has been a violation of the Con
stitution of the United States, and that
steps detrimental to "life, liberty, and
property" have been taken "without
due process of law."
Berger Resolution.
The Berger resolution Is follows:
"Whereas, tho fourteenth amend
ment to the Constitution ordaln3
that no State shall 'deprive any
person of life, liberty, or property
without due process of law, nor deny
any person within its Jurisdiction
the equal protection of the laws, and
"Whereas. It is reported In the
public press that one John J. Mc
Namaran heretofore residing in the
city of Indianapolis, Ind.. has been
deprived of Uberty and put In jeop
ardy of his life without due process
of law; therefore, bo It
"Resolved by the House of Repre
sentatives (the Senate concurring)
that a committee of each house bo
appointed to Investigate the arrest
and extradition of the said Mc
Namara, and to report its tlndlngs to
the two houpes at the earliest prac
ticable moment."
In the Senate it Is expected that the
Senate Third Degree Investigating Com
mittee will probe the tactics utcd In se
curing the alleged confession of Mc
Manigal. Senator Brandegee's attention
was called to the statement that Mc
aianigal withstood a constant charge of
questions for twelve hours before he
broke down and told his story.
A representative of the committee al
ready has discussed with President
Gompers the tactics used in securing
the statement, and it is expected the of
ficial probe of the circumstances will be
started with the next meeting of the
"I cannot say what steps will be
taken said Senator Brandegee, the
chairman of the commission, this morn
ing, "because our committee mis not
met since the facts have been dis
closed." Leaders Gone.
Considerable Interest Is beine taken
today over the activity of the Ameri
can Federation ot Labor, because
President Gompers and Secretary Wil
liam J. Spencer of the building trades'
branch of the federation, have left
Washington. At Mr. Gompers' offlce
it was stated he had gone to New
York to fill an engagement some time
ago, but no one at Mr. Spencer's offlce
was prepared to say whether he had
accompanied Mr. Gompers.
Secretary Frank Morrison said he
did not know what had called Mr.
Spencer from the city, but was sure
Mr. Gompers' absence was not the
result of the new labor troubles.
That the American Federation of La
bor stands ready to send out an appeal
to all its affiliated bodies as soon as
assistance Is asked for McNamara has
been learned here. When the big strug
gle for the organization of labor along
the Pacific coast reached its climax
some time ago an appeal was made and
$600,000 raised. It is expected that the
appeal now pending will bring an
equally large amount.
No Official Advices.
According to Secretary Morrison, the
Federation has received no official ad
vice of all that has happened In Indian
apolis, and tho officers do not propose
to make public any more of their plans
until some positive Information is re
ceived. When shown the first statement of
Detective William J. Burns as to how
he secured the evidence he expects will
(Continued on Twelfth Page.)
McNamara on Fast
Train Near Denver
En Route to Coast City
VKSVKr.. Colo.. Apr!' 25. Fleeing1
from possible legal intervention in
the shape of habeas corpus writs, the
eleven detectives guarding John 3.
McNamara, his brother, James W., and
Ortie E. McManigal today are speed
ing toward Los Angeles on Santa Fe
train No. 3. They t-hould reach Los
Angeles on Thursday.
John J McNamara was taken from
Indianapolis on a. Missouri Pacific
train bound for the Coast, while
James W. McNamara and McManigal
were started West on the Santa Fe
train. They all arrived at La Junta,
Colo., late last night on the same
Santa Fe train.
John J. McNamara had been taken
from tho Missouri Pacific train at Hols
ington, Kan., where an automobile was
waiting. In company with detectives
and armed guards, he was rushed to
Great Bend, Kan., where he was placed
on the Santa Fe train which bore his
brother and 'McManigal.
The three prisoners are kept In thtt
drawing room of the Pullman, each
manacled to a detective, while other
detectives armed with automatic pis
tols and Winchester rifles, are constant
ly on guard both to prevent an escape
and to r.eslst an attempt to rescue the
prisoners.
No one Is allowed to enter the draw
ing room. When they sleep, tho
prisoners are kept chained to a de
tective James W. McNamara has not
even been allowed to shave since his
arrest In Detroit, the detectives de
claring they fear an attempt at
suicide.
It is hardly probable tho men will
bo taken into Los Angeles on tho
train. It Is understood an automo
bile will be watting fifty or sixty
miles out, and that the prisoners will
be smuggled into the city secretly.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88085187/1911-04-26/ed-1/?sp=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>BURNS MUST
TELL STORY
Detective Burns Arrested in Indiana
polis Must Tell Grand Jury What
He Knows—Friends Will Try To
Have McNamara Taken Back.
(IJy United Press Leased Wire.)
INDIANAPOLIS. April 26.
Determined to fight to the last
ditch for John J. McNamara, in
ternational secretary of the Struc
tural Ironworkers, accused of in
spiring dynamite explosions in
Los Angfles, labor leaders here to
day launched a plan to undo the
so-called "kidnaping" of McXa
mara and force his return here
from the California city.
Acting on advice by Clarence
Darrow, whose work acquitted
Moyer, Hay wood and Pettibone of
charges of inspiring the assassi
nation of former Qov. Steunen
berg of Idaho, telegrams were
sent to Congressman Korbly and
•Senators Shively and Kern of In
diana asking them to introduce
resolutions in congress to inves
tigate the details of the manner
In which McNamara was spirited
out of Indianapolis and rushed
to the west.
Burns to Tell AH.
As a part of this plan. Detec
tive William J. Burns, who was
arrested here last night, charged
with having inspired McNamara's
kidnaping, was taken before the
grand jury today and is expected
to reveal to these lnqulßltorg in
full the developments which led
to the removal of Mc.Vamara. It
is probable that the grand jury
will first hear all evidence from
Burns regarding the alleged find
ing of dynamite before consider
ing the kidnaping proper.
Legal experts here declare that
Darrow's .plan to force the return
of McNamara from Los Angeles
is entirely feasible. The fact
that it is not contended that Mc-
Namara was in California at all
at or immediately prevlouß to
the explosion at the Los Angeles
Times, which crime he is accused
of plotting, will, they say, prove
a big obstacle to the Burns'
forces efforts to force the labor
leader to trial in the California
courts.
Darrow's contention will be
that, as McNatnara's rights have
been invaded, it is only just that
he should be restored to his posi
tion before the law prior to that
Invasion.
EXCITEMENT IN LOS ANGELES
(By United Press Leased Wire.)
BARSTOW, CM., April SW.—
Tin" two McNamara brothers and
Ortie McManfgal, in the custody
of a dozen detectives, passed
through here at 9:45 this morn
ing on their way to Ijos Angeles.
IjOS ANGELES, April 26.—
With John J. and James W. Mc-
Namara and Ortle McManigal,
speeding toward Los Angeles,
but a few miles out of the city,
the situation In Los Angeles,
where the brothers are wanted
for alleged complicity in the de
struction of the Los Angeles
Times plant, and McManigal, or
alleged dynamiting of the Llewel
lyn Ironworks, was tense today.
While' prison trustees were fur
nishing up three cells in widely
separated parts of the county Jail
for the prisoners' reception, rep
resentatives of the 'district attor
ney's office and Chief of Police
Sebastian conferred as to the best
plan of slipping the suspects Into
the city.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn87093220/1911-12-04/ed-1/?sp=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>THE McNAMARAS CONFESS
LOS ANGELES MURDERS
James B. McNamara, Man Who Blew Up The Times, Which
Carried With It The Death of Twenty-one
Employes.
CONFESS IN HOPE OF ESCAPING DEATH PENALTY
John J. McNamara, the One Who Destroyed Llewellyn Iron
Works-One Escapes With Life Sentence, Other
Probably With Fourteen Years
LOS ANGELES, Dec I.—James B. McNamara pleaded guilty to murder
ill tht; first, degree in .Judge Walter Bordwell's court today. His brother,
John J. McNamara, secretary of the International Association of Bridge
and Structural Iron Workers, entered a plea of guilty to dynamiting the
Llewellyn Iron Works in Los Angeles, Christmas day, 1910.
Clears Entire Tragedy
James B. McNamara's confession clears up absolutely the tragedy ot
the explosion and lire which, at 1:07 o'clock on the morning of October 1,
1910, wrecked the plant of the Los Angeles Times, at First and Broadway,
and caused the death of twenty-one persons. For nineteen of these "deaths
the McNamara brothers were indicted, and I. B. McNamara was on trial
specifically for the murder of Charles .1. Haggerty, a machinists whose
body was found nearer than that of any other to the spot where the dyna
mite was supposed to have been placed.
Will Be Sentenced December 5
Both men's sentences were set for December 5, when it is expected Dis
trict Attorney John 1. Fredericks will ask for life imprisonment for James
B. McNamara, the confessed murderer, and probably fourteen years for his
brother. 'I lie men's lives are considered saved. The great contention that
the Los Angeles Times was not dynamited is dead beyond resurrection or
any argument.
Tonight as the two brothers sat together in the county jail, refusing to
see anyone or to make any statement, an interest second to the occurrence
itself hung about the question with reference to James 8., "Why did he
confess?"
To this opposing counsel gave the same answer.
Confessed Because of Guilt
"He confessed because he was guilty, and that's all there is to it," de
clared District Attorney Fredericks.
"He was counseled to confess because that was the best thing he could
do in opinion of counsel," said Attorney Clarence S. Darrow, chief of coun
sel. "I will say now that there was no other reason or motive in it. I have
studied this case for months. It presented a stone wall."
Darrow's statement was made after looking square in the face of charge*
that the recent arrest of Burt H. Franklin, an investigator employed by the
defense, and two others with him, might have precipitated a situation un
tenable, save by confession of the prisoner.
Burns Still on Job
CHICAGO, Dec. 2. —Detective William J. Burns left Chicago tonight to take
up anew the trail he hopes soon to end with the arrest of every man con
nected with the McNamara dynamiting gang. The detective refused to di
vulge his destination, but it is believed he went to Indianapolis.
Before his departure he intimated that the result of the guilty pleas
entered by the McNamara brothers might mean further arrests in San Fran
cisco. He refused to make predictions as to when the arrests would come,
"Burns is still on the job," he said, with a smile, as he brushed a pile
of congratulatory telegrams aside and picked up a telephone to give several
last orders to subordinates in Chicago. "We've got the evidence —overwhelm
ing evidence —to prove just who was concerned in this entire matter, and
we 11 get the men before we quit. That's about all I can say."
"That means the men who employed the McNamara gang that blew up
the Los Angeles Times building?" was suggested. "Do you know them?
"We know who they are. We know they will be arrested and others
will be arrested who have a hand in the labor plots in connection with
the Structural Iron Workers, Milton A. Schmidt and David Caplan, the other
two men under indictment in connection with the Times explosion, will be
arrested before we are done.
Believes Others Being Protected
"They are being protected right now by the McNamara defense, but
they will be found. I know they are in this country."
"Do you think the discovery of the jury bibery plot in Los Angeles had
anything to do with the pleas entered by the McNamaras?" he was asked.
"We have all the facts in connection with that plot," he answered,
smiling. "We know all about it."
The detective said the statement of Attorney Clarence Darrow to the
effect that James B. McNamara declared he did not expect such a heav>
explosion and insisted that force was greater because of a co-ordinate ev
plosion of gas. was in keeping with the confession of Ortie McManigal, who
helped commit the crime.
Knew Part of Explosion Due to Gas
"Why, McManigal told us in his first confession that McNamara turned
open the stop cocks on ihe gas mains of the building when he set the bomb,'
the detective said. "We knew all the time that a part of the explosion was
due to the gas, but they had plenty of dynamite and nitroglycerine there
to wreck the building, at that. They tried to buy 90 per cent, dynamite to
do the job, and when told that 85 per cent, was the strongest they could
buy, they got that. The statement that ten or twelve pounds of dynamite
was all they had may or may not be true. They had hundreds of pounds
at their command."
Says Samuel Gompers Lied
Speaking of Samuel Gompers. against whom the detective has the most
bitter feeling because of the labor head's denunciation of the detective and
his methods. Mr. Burns said:
"Gompers knew from the first that 1 never made a 'plant' of dynamite,
as he has charged. How do 1 know? Because Clarence Darrow told him
so in Indianapolis immediately after the arrests were made. Darrow told
him right then that Burns never 'planted' the dynamite and that 1 had
a case."
Fight Has Only Begun
NE W YORK, Dec. 2.—"The fight has only just begun. This is only the
lirst chapter. What we want to find out now is who were the men behind
the McNamaras. and this we purpose doing."
This statement was made today by Walter Drew, chief counsel for the
National Erectors' association, which employed William J. Burns and his
detectives to investigate the Los Angeles dynamiting case.
"The McNamaras in pleading guilty have said that they were sent on'
there and acted for a principle," Mr. Drew continued. "It is obvious that
the men representing this 'principle' have kept them well supplied with
money. It is to find out who these men are that becomes the important
issue from now on."
McNamaras Only Tools
"The McNamaras," continued Mr. Drew, "were merely tools of a coteri.
of men who attempted by force to coerce builders of structural steel an
bridges into maintaining a closed shop and as hirelings they had no interest,
whatever in committing murder or blowing up property further than to s
j do their work as to draw their pay.
"Their crimes are nominal compared to those committed by the men wh
sent, them lo do these jobs and who paid for murdering men and destroying
j buildings and bridges with high explosives.
"These are the men we want, and I believe that when the Unite i
States grand jury again assembles in Indianapolis events will transpire whit
i will make the confessions of the McNamaras' puny by comparison."
Mr, Drew told how, five years ago, his association had undertaken t
put ait end to the dynamiting of its construction work, and how William
Burns had been called in to work on the case.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn92053934/1912-02-14/ed-1/?sp=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>DYNAMITERS
BY SCORE ARE
BEHIND BARS
Take Iron Workers Offi-
cers and Agents in Nu
merous Cities.
IN A BIG CONSPIRACY
Association Has Already Accu
mulated Fund to Defend
Accused Men.
Indianapolis, Feb. 14. Arrests in the
dynamite conspiracy cases began to
day and most of the CO or more de
fendants in various parts of the coun
try were taken into custody. One of
tiie first arrests here was Frank M.
Ryan, president of the International
Association of Bridge and Structural
Iron Workers. Eleven business agents
of the iron workers, four or Ave offi
cials and some members of the execu
tive board who are charged with know
ing what McNamara did with money
used to buy explosives, are among
those indicted.
WKBB SHOW McMAXIGAL.
An important arrest was Frank C.
Wfbb, former member of the iron
workers' executive board, taken in New
York, who figures prominently in Ortie
McManlgaTs confession. Webb is
charged with meeting Mc.Manlgal and
showing him where to do "Jobs" in
Hoboken and Jersey City. Houlihan,
arrested in Chicago, is charged with
furthering violation of :he federal stat
utes in connection w ith an explosion at
South Chicago, and by assisting Mc
Manlgal, the confessed dynamiter.
HOf Kl A TRAILER.
John T. Butler of BufTalo, N. Y, first
vice president of the iron workers;
Herbert S. Hockln of Detroit, second
vice president and acting secretary
treasurer, and Fred Sherman, local bus
iness agent, were arrested here after
Ryan was taken. Hockln succeeded J.
J. McNamara as secretary-treasurer.
McManlgal in his confession charged
Hockln was the "man who put him in
the dynamiting business." It Is charg.
ed Hockln went to Detroit in June,
1907, and Induced McManlgal to take
up dynamiting.
iwrKi chief likitexaxt.
In the information supplied the gov
rrnmpnf llorkln is mulf to nnnpar im
chief lieutenant of John J. McNamsra.
He is charged with having planned ex
plosions desired by enemies of "open
shop" contractors. McManigal names
him as one of the men who originated
the alarm clock scheme for timing ex
plosions. He is also charged with be
ing the manager of secret stores of
explosives kept at Rochester, Pa.,
H uncle, Ind., Tiffin, Ohio, and Indian
apolis. AGENTS OP VAST CONSPIRACY.
Engene A. Clancy of San Francisco;
J. E. Munsey. Salt Lake City; Olf A.
Tveltmoe, San Francisco; Ortie Mc
Manlgal, already Indicted on the Pa
cific coast, and J. J. McNamara and
James B. McNamara, already convict
ed, are sgaln indicted here. In the in
dictments It is held the McNamara
brothers and McManlgal were merely
Agents of vast conspiracy. AU the
defendants are .charged with a con
spiracy to transport dynamite and
nitroglycerin in violation of the fed
eral statutes.
HYAX ELECTED IW 1SOS.
Ryan was elected president of the
International Iron Workers' union in
1905, succeeding Frank Buchanan, now
a congressman from Chicago. Soon af
ter It became known his officials were
to be Indicted Ryan asked the union to
establish a special fund of $7,000 a
month. It !s believed this fund will
cow be utilized for defense at the
trials. The Iron workers' union, whose
headquarters are in Indianapolis, has
about 13,000 members with 107 local
unions in the United States and Can
ada.
Ryan and Hockln this afternoon
Issued statements declaring their In
nocence.
blows rr opera Horse.
M. J. Young, arrested 1n Boston, Is
accused of assisting McManlgal to
blow up part of the Boston opera house
In March. 1909, and to have sent Mc
Manlgal to Springfield, 'Mass., whe
part of the municipal buildings were
destroyed.
Among those released on bond of
$10,000 each are: Ryan, Hockln, But
ler; $5,000, Morrln, Cunnane.
HOVLIHAX GIVES VP.
Chicago. Feb. 14. Richard H. Houll
ban, a labor leader Indicted at Indian
polls, was arrested here today. Houl
ihan made no attempt to escape offi
cers throughout yesterday, when
It
was reported he would be arrested
He was at his office. He said he would
surrender whenever the authorities
called for him. But they failed to
come to his office.
KAHLY MORNING VISITS
Reports were current last night that
the indicted men would be arrested at
heir homes, and again Houlihan an
nounced himself ready for arrest. He
remained np late awaiting the arrival
of the officers. They did not come un
til nearly daylight.
THREE OTHERS TAKES.
Houlihan is financial secretary of
the Chicago local Bridge and Structur
al Iron Workers. His offices are in
this city. Three other labor leaders
were arrested .at the same time as
Houlihan. News of Houlihan's arrest
came from his wife. All the prisoners
were taken to the federal building and
secreted.
Besides Houlihan, the men arrest
ed here are James Coughlin, James
Conney and William Schoupe, mem
bers of the Iron Workers' union. The
two last named are business agents.
1 Four men arrested here were re
leased later on bonds of $5,000 each
to appear in Indianapolis March 12.
ARRESTS IN OTHER CITIES.
Other arrests reported, based on
Indianapolis indictments, are:
Milwaukee W. E. Redding. Her
man G. Seffert.
Kansas City, Mo. W. Bert Brown,
W. J. McCain.
Brown was the iron workers' busi
ness agent in August, 1910, at the time
of the $1,000,000 Armour, Swift, and
the Burlington bridge over the Mis
souri river here were dynamited. Mc
Cain succeeded him.
Cleveland, Ohio Peter J. Smith, for
merly business agent, and George
("Nipper") Anderson, said to have
been walking delegate of the iron work
ers. Denver, Col. Henry W. Legleltner,
formerjy.a member of the L.eieuJf
board of the iron workers.
IJAVF.NPORTER ON LIST.
Davenport, Iowa Daniel Buckley,
business agent of the local iron workers.
Scrsnton, Pa. M. J. Hannon, former
local business agent of the Iron work
ers, now agent of the Central Labor
union.
Duluth, Minn. Fred Mooney, con
nected with the iron workers' union.
Springfield, 111. A. J. Kavanaugh and
M. L. Fennel.
St. Louis John Barry, former
walking delegate of the Bridge and
Structural Iron Workers, and Paul
Morrln, active in raising the defense
fund for the McNamaras.
PEORIA N I.N NET.
Peoria, 111. Ed Smyth and James
E. Rain, both released on $5,000
bond each.
Boston Michael J. Young, mem
ber of the executive board and pres
ident of the Boston local union
No. 7.
Syracuse, N. Y. John R. Carroll
of the iron workers.
Minneapolis, Minn. Charles N.
Beum, business agent and secretary
of the Minneapolis Building Trades
council.
Detroit, Mich. Charles W. Wach-
meistern, Frank J. Murphy.
Indianapolis Spurgeon P. Mead
ows, business agent of the Interna
tional Brotherhood of Carpenters
end Joiners.
New York Frank C. Webb, for
mer member of the executive board
of the Structural Iron Workers, and
Patrick E. Farrell.
Brooklyn, N. Y., Daniel Brophy.
Philadelphia Michael J. Cuname,
business agent of the Structural Iron
orkers.
RYAN HELD AT INDIANAPOLIS.
Indianapolis, Feb. 14. Frank M.
Ryan, president of the International
Association of Bridge and Structural
Iron Workers, was arrested here this
morning on indictments returned in
the dynamite conspiracy.
WALKING DELEGATE AND AGENT.
Cincinnati. Ohio. Feb. 14. Edward
Clark and Ernest G. W. Basey were
arrested today on Indictments returned
by the federal gTand Jury at Indian
apolis, charging violation of the inter
state commerce law governing trans
portation of dynamite. Clark Is a for
mer w alking delegate end Basey a for
mer business agent of the International
Association of 'Bridge and Structural
Iron Workers.
FORMER SECRETARY HELD.
Syracuse, N. Y, Feb. 14. E. E.
Phillips, former secretary of the Bridge
and Structural Iron Workers' union,
was arrested here this morning.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85032923/1913-01-01/ed-1/?sp=4</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>NOTABLE VICTORY FOR GOVERNMENT IN
THE DYNAMITE CONSPIRACY CASE
Affecting Scenes in the Court Room
When the Verdicts of Guilty
Are Returned
By Associated Press.
INDIANAPOLIS, Dec. 28. The government with stern, decisive
swiftness today took into possession thirty-eight union labor officials,
convicted of conspiracy in prompting explosions on non-union work through
out the land, aiding the destruction which brought the loss of life at
Los Angeles and carrying on a "reign of terror," declared to be unparal
leled in the history of the country.
Almost the entire executive staff of the International Association
of Bridge, structural and Iron Workers was convicted. Only two- offi
cials of that union now remain out of jaiL At the head of the list of
those convicted stands Frank M. Ryan, the president It was in this
Union, with its twelve thousand members, that John J. McNamara was
Secretary-Treasurer, while, he conducted the dynamitings out of which
the present convictions grew.
Today's convictions, on a scale
unprecedented in a Federal court are
the aftermath of the killing of twenty-one
persons in the explosion of
the Los Angeles Times. McNamara
and his brother, James B., the Times
dynamiters, convicted in California,
are now in San Quentin penitentiary.
Ryan and his fellow officials, the
former associates of McNamara, are
now Federal prisoners, awaiting sen
tence. Two convicted, not affiliated with
the Iron Workers, were found
guilty of promoting the conspiracy.
Sixteen minutes in all was the
time required by the court to re
ceive the jury, read the verdict of
"thirty-eight guilty" and dismiss the
jurors. The verdict brought to an
end the history of the dynamite trial.
It meant, except in the cases of
Herman G. Seiffert, of Milwaukee,
and Daniel Buckley, of Davenport,
Iowa, the two found "not guilty,"
that the government's charges about
the dynamite plots extending, over
six years, were sustained. I'meant.
also, that thirty wives, -Inany with"
their children, who -sat patiently
through the long ordeal, would at
last be separated from their hus
bands. Important details yet remain in
consequence of the verdicts. Pun
ishments are to be imposed on the
thirty-eight men by Federal Judge
Anderson Monday morning at ten
o'clock. The prisoners who receive
terms longer than a year will be
taken to the Federal prison at Leav
enworth, Kansas. A special train
will take them by a secret route.
Details as to its leaving Indianapolis
and arrival in Leavenworth will not
be made public It is learned that
United States Marshall Edward
Schmidt, who is to accompany the
prisoners, already had prepared for;
the special which will leave as soon
as possible after the sentences. A
delay in the arrangement may be
caused by appeals which may actj
as a stay of execution of the court's j
judgment.
Thirty-nine and a half years is
the maximum punishment for any
one prisoner in this case. It may
vary from the maximum to any
shorter imprisonment or fine the
court wishes to impose.
Motions and appeals will be made
Monday. Senator Kern, now in
Washington and William Harding,
another attorney for the defense,
stated motions in behalf of all the
men will be offered. District At
torney Miller said he would oppose
any appeals for light sentences in
the cases of certain prisoners. To
night the prisoners, four in each
cell, otcupy two tiers of cells in the
Marion county jail. The prisoners
were handcuffed after the courtroom
was cleared of spectators, and be
teween deputy marshalls, marched
five blocks through the streets in
the brilliant winter sunlight to the
county jail. An hour after their ar
rival they were served the regular
noonday meal, a half loaf of bread,
tin of coffee, beef and cabbage. The
prisoners, visible one to another
through the bars were variously
downcast and cheerful. Some pro
fessed to take the verdict in light
spirits, while disappointment was
plainly written on the countenances
of others.
Extra guards were placed about
the jail to prevent a demonstration
by crowds. Wives and children of
the prisoners were ordered with oth
er spectators out of the court room
where some wept when the verdict
was rendered and attempted to climb
the railing separating them from
their husbands. Later in the streets
they struggled through the crowds
trying to follow their husbands to
jail. All the afternoon .attorneys
and women relatives .divided the
time of the prisoners.
President Ryan wss interviewed in
the jail tonight. "I have nothing to
say but this," said Ryan. "Greater
men than we have been incarcerated.
In olden time they cut off the ears
of honest men."
The Los Angeles Cases.
LOS ANGELES, Dec 28. "What
will be done with McManigal" was
the question put tonight to District
Attorney Fredericks who prosecut
ed the McNamaras.
"That will be a story for another
day," Fredercicks answered. "He
will be back here soon, but I cannot
discuss him now. I will say though,
that without his testimony and as
sistance tLere would, have been no
case at Indianapolis.''
Federal officials said the three in
dictments of four counts each which
alleged the illegal transportation of
explosives against Tveitmoe, Clancy
and Munsey, returned a year ago
here, are still in effect. Action has
been postponed from time to time,
awaiting the result at Indianapolis.
They are now due to come up in the
Federal court on January 13th, but
their disposition either as to dis
missal or setting for trial, depend up
on the orders of Attorney General
Wickersham. Anton Johannsen, the
San Francisco labor leader, indicted
here, but not at Indianapolis, will
probably be tried here it is said.
The thrity-cight defendants found
guilty follow:
Frank M. Ryan, president of the
International Association of Bridge
and Structural Irpn Workers' Union.
John T. Butler, of Buffalo, vice-
president.
Herbert S. Hockin, vice-president,
formerly of Detroit.
Olaf A. Tveitmoe, of San Fran
Cisco, secretary of the California
Building Trades Council.
Eugene A. Clancey, of San Fran
cisco. Philip A. Cooley, of New Orleans.
Michael J. Young and Frank K.
Higgins of Boston.
J. E. Munsey, of Salt Lake City,
Frank C. Webb and Patrick F.
Farrell, of New York.
John H. Barry and Paul J. Morris
of St Louis.
Henry W. Legleitner of Denver.
Charles N. Beura, of Minneapolis,
William E. Reddin, of Milwaukee
Michael J. Cunnane, of Philadel
phia.
Richard H. Houlihan, James Coon
ey, James A. Coughlin and William
Shupe, of Chicago.
Edward Smythe, of Peoria.
James E. Rhea, of Illinois.
Murray L. Pennell, of Springfield.
William Bernhardt, of Cincinnati.
Wilford B. Broun and William J.
McCain of Kansas City.
Frank K. Painter, of Omaha.
Peter J. Smith and George Ander
son, of Cleveland.
Michael J. Hannon, of Scranton.
Edward E. Phillips, of Syracuse.
Charles Watchmeisrer and Frank
J. Murphy, of Detroit
Fred J. Mooney, of Duluth.
Ernest G. W. Basey, of Indianapo
lis.
Fred Sherman, of Indianapolis.
'Hiram R. Kline, of Muncie.
HISTORY OF THE
DYNAMITE CASE.
INDIANAPOLIS, Ind.. Dec 28.
It was a scene blended with tragedy
that confronted those who week
after week sat through the historic
dynamite conspiracy" trials.
Now it was a baby crying from
the rear of the court room, where
the wives and children of the de
fendants sat; now it was the heavy
voice of a man seated in. the wit
ness chair and defending .himself
against the charges of a nation-wide
conspiracy, in which officials of union
labor were 'deeply concerned. Wit
nesses from near and far came and
went, but those whose fate rested
with the jury remained there, listen
ing to the accusations and to the
oft-repeated story of the killing of
twenty-one people in the Los An
geles "Times" explosion.
The court room itself seemed a
fitting setting for that sombre story.
Surrounded by great marble pillars,
with the daylight shut out by heavy
curtains, and the judge installed be
fore an allegorical painting of Jus-
tice, that court room day after day
echoed the stories of violence, of
the discovery of burnt fuses and
bursted infernal machines, of mid
night visits of mysterious men in
alleys, in empty houses, in lonely
country roads, or on the tops of
buildings.
The vision of a dark spectre with
a bomb under his arm became a
familiar image in the minds of those
who listened.- Back of the railings,
amid the spectators, sat the relatives
of the defendants. Three rows deep
across the room were the defend
ants. Among the the score of at
torneys sat perhaps the most pictur
esque defendant, massive in build,
florid in complexion, always studi-'
ously occupied, now copiously filling
his note-ljook when the testimony
was exciting; now, when the trial
lagged, burying his spectacled nose
in a Latin version of Omar Khay-
yam. He was Olaf A. Tveitmoe of
San Francisco.
Another in toward whom the
eyes of the spectators often strayed
was Herbert S. Hockin. He sat
apart, between bailiffs, during much
of the trial, for he had been branded
by the court as. a man who could
not be trusted by any one." It was
Hockin who was named as having
promoted the dynamiting business;
it was Hockin who was accused of
"holding out" on the pay of the
dynamiters; it was he who was said
to have caused a quarrel in the ranks
of the McNamaras and McManigal,
and it was he who finally was charg
ed with betraying for his own gain"
those with whom he once associated,
and with whom he was affiliated in
the iron workers' union.
Gray-haired and old beyond his
years sat Frank M. Ryan, president
(Continued on Page Five)
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn78002169/1941-03-09/ed-1/seq-5/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>James McNamara Dies
In San Quentin Prison
SAN QUENTIN, Calif., March 8.
—UP—James B. McNamara, 59,
who pleaded guilty to murder of
one of the 21 persons killed in the
Los Angeles Times bombing Oct.
1, 1910, died today in San Quentin
prison.
McNamara and his brother,
John J., were indicted for murder
of 19 of the 21 Times employes
who perished in the explosion and
subsequent fire. John admitted
dynamiting the Llewellyn Iron
Works in Los Angeles on Christ
mas Day, 1910. 
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1941-03-09/ed-1/seq-18</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>McNamara, Figure
In Los Angeles Times
Blast, Dies in Prison
Attempt to Free Him Made
By Notables; Anti-Union
Fight Preceded Dynamiting
B the Associated Press.
SAN QUENTIN, Calif., March 8 —
James B. McNamara, 59, who plead
ed guilty to murder of one of the
21 persons killed in the Los Angeles
Times bombing October 1, 1910, died
today in San Quentin Prison.
McNamara and his brother, John
J„ were indicted for murder of 19
of the 21 Times employes who per
ished in the explosion and sub
sequent fire. John admitted dyna
miting the Llewellyn Iron Works
in Los Angeles Christmas Day, 1910.
The late Clarence Darrow. chief
of the McNamara defense staff, said
James “was counseled to confess
because that was the best thing he
could do, in the opinion of his
counsel.” James indicated he
pleaded guilty to save his brother.
"Joe (John) is not in on this deal,”
he said.
James w!as sentenced to life im
prisonment. John was given 15
years but was released after serv
ing nine years in San Quentin.
contracted under war and economic
pressure, these regions lay on the |
ancient east-west path of conquest.
Once the hub of the vast domain
of Alexander theGreat. Macedonia
became part of the Turkish Empire i
in the 14th century. Later, in the
Balkan war of 1912. it was parti
tioned between Bulgaria, Greece
and Serbia: and still later tin post
World War settlements'* it was di
vided again between Yugoslavia and
Greece.
“Ancient Thrace, whose Greek
section now extends south of Bul
garia and west of Turkey to form
the end of the Grecian panhandle,
was invaded by Darius, Xerxes ar.d
Philip of Macedonia. A Roman
province, it was at various times
also under the Goths and the Huns,
and with the rest of the Balkan
states fell to the conquering hordes
of the Turks.
“Like Macedonia. Thrace was for
centuries a non-melting pot of con
flicting nationals, where disputed
boundaries, local economics, tradi
tion and language combined to make
for trouble between the assorted
peoples who lived there.
Prison records indicated he now
lives at Fortville, Ind.
In 1936, 48 prominent per
sons, including Mr. Darrow. Senator
Nye of North Dakota, Theodore
Dreiser, Upton Sinclair, Sinclair
Lewis and Warden Lewis E. Lawes
of Sing Sing Prison, petitioned
Frank F. Merriam. then Governor
of California, to pardon McNamara.
McNamara served 25 years at San
Quentin and five at Folsom Prison
and was returned to San Quentin
last February 13. At that time he i
told Warden Clinton Duffy:
“I came back to San Quentin
Prison to die.”
The Times bombing occurred at j
1:07 a.m. while editorial and shop;
workers were at their jobs. It was |
described as retaliation against the
paper's vigorous fight against the |
union closed shop.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1957-04-14/ed-1/seq-117</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Jerry Giesler, Courtroom Gladiator,
Soothes and Saves the Harried Stars
By JULIAN HARTT
HOLLYWOOD (NANAI—
The motion picture business
didn’t know it at the time,
but one of its best reasons
for settling in the suburb of
Hollywood could well have
been that attorney Jerry
Giesler already was here.
For the past 30 years of As
nearly half a century in prac
tice, Jerry Giesler has been
the courtroom marine corps,
the legal gladiator, who has
beaten back again and again
those most terrible of threats
to stardom: Shame, scandal
and prison terms.
Marie (The Body) McDon
ald was the latest to utter the
traditional movie colony cry
of desperation—“ Get Giesler!"
—when her account of kid
naping and half-clad aban
donment in the desert was met
more with suspicion than in
vestigation. And the mere
fact that Jerry Giesler ac
cepted the case brought in
stant change. Officers who had
spoken previously of possible
“false reports" suddenly
brought a measure of defer
ence to that still-stalemated
inquiry.
Just who is Jerry Giesler?
At first sight and sound, a
courtroom spectator or pros
pective juror might be inclined
to smile, to feel that here is a
successful but perhaps slightly
too-dapper small-town busi
nessman. He moves swiftly
and purposefully into any
room, usually wearing two
tone shoes, that frequently in
clude suede in their pattern.
His portly figure is securely
buttoned into a double
breasted suit, in which his
(r
BBii*:-''--' mamma
LAUREN BACALL
As Free as the Breeze
made a trip to New York in
a year and half. I thought the
trip would be good for me to
get me out of town. I love
my role in ‘Designing Woman.’
and dammit. I want to bask in
it. I think it's the best I ever
did.
"I’ve been thinking about
doing a play for a long time.
I was to have done ‘The Last
Tycoon’ on television with Bo
gey, but I wouldn’t do it with
out him. Now I’d like to con
centrate on pictures for about
18 months. I’m dying to work.
I’ve always been a working
girl. It took a few years after
I married Bogey for me to be
sure that I wanted to work.
But I’m glad I never accepted
pictures that would have taken
me away from him. Blood
Alley.’ with two weeks of loca
tion in San Francisco, was the
farthest away I ever went from
Bogey. And, as you know, he
came up there to see me.”
The Bogarts formed Maple
ton Productions, "but I have
no interest in producing." said
Lauren. "I just love to act, and
I’m happy to have the man
have the biggest part.” This
could explain the success of
to Humphrey
Bog Mt.
Stamps—Camera—Art
Records —Bridge
taste runs to pinstripes. Gie
sler’s shirts are plain-colored,
and his ties conservative but
colorful. And when he sweeps
off his snap-brimmed hat, he
does it with the backward mo
tion of a man who is conscious
of the grooming of his thin
ning hair.
When he speaks, there is
another surprise. His voice is
thin, high-pitched and seem
ingly always on the verge of
cracking, but it never quite
does.
Picture of Dignity
These first impressions are
swiftly forgotten, however, as
he goes into action. Then the
Jerry Giesler of legal renown
becomes clear. His pale blue
eyes convey at once the as
surance of full and complete
frankness and honesty.
In court he is the picture
of dignity. No witness ever is
heckled or badgered with sar
casm. no matter how greatly
the counsel might be tempted
by the situation.
For behind Jerry Giesler’s
extreme courtesy is a keen
mind, deftly leading the wit
ness down a seemingly inno
cent path of interrogation to
the brink of disaster. His skill
is such that fellow lawyers
usually pack the spectators'
section to watch and learn.
Giesler was bom 69 years
ago in the small community of
Wilton Junction, lowa, and
spent his boyhood in Musca
tine. where his father was a
banker.
He had his law degree, but
still was little more than a
briefcase-carrier when, in 1910,
the noted Attorney Clarence
Darrow was charged with brib
BROADWAY
Men Made a Mistake,
Eartha Kitt Declares
Bv WILLIAM GLOVER
NEW YORK, WP._"You
men.” purred Eartha Kltt with
a grin mixed of mischief and
mockery, “made a mistake
letting women get so far.”
Broadway's sultry singer
dancer arched up on her toes,
stared intently in the mirror,
flecked a hand over cheek and
hair.
She was busy explaining her
first musical comedy. "Shin
bone Alley" which officially
opened last night), separating
the off-stage Eartha from the
on-stage Kitt, and comment
ing on more or less related
matters.
"Women are too confused to
have any philosophy other
than a natural instinct for
survival,” she continued, "but
they're learning more than
they used to.
"Now they know how to.
handle men—to neutralize
them. That's where you men
made a mistake."
Catlike Grare
Looking mildly pleased, she
postured llthely into a new
crouch on her chair. There
was something faintly—and
fittingly—feline in every word,
tone and gesture.
Miss Kitt's catlike grace and
aura is being applied in
"Shinbone Alley” to portrayal
of the famous cat mehitabel,
who along with archie the
cockroach, was immortalized
in the allegories of Don Mar
quis. Archie is personified by
Eddie Bracken in the show.
Eartha firmly distinguishes
between herself and her stage
Incarnation.
“I think mehitabel thinks
ntore deeply than most worn-
Antlnued on I’age E-11, Col. I
K
ing a juror in the celebrated
Los Angeles Times bombing
case. During Darrow's trial,
Earl Rogers, defending him,
sent Giesler to look up a point
in question.
Both Giesler’s employer and
the impressive client were
amazed when he returned with
40 pages of thorough research.
In mid-trial Giesler was boost
ed to associate counsel and
made one of the attorneys of
record.
With the acquittal of Dar
row, Jerry Geisler’s name was
added to that of Rogers on
the office door. But nearly
two decades of broadening,
seasoning in the catch-as
catch-can field of high-pow
ered criminal law cases
remained ahead before Holly
wood swept Giesler into its
arms as its chosen advocate.
There was the grimly re
membered education of the
Jess Willard case, when the
fighter was tried on man
slaughter charges after an
opponent. Bull Young, was fa
tally injured in a bout.
Rogers had led Giesler to
believe he would make the
closing address to the jury
right up to the moment it was
scheduled, then announced:
“Mr. Giesler will address
the jury!”
The Turning Point
Without an iota of prepara
tion. Giesler got to his feet as
Rogers stalked out of the
courtroom, leaving him in the
make-or-break situation.
Giesler began talking. He
talked for three hours. And
the verdict was “Not guilty.”
Jerry Giesler calls the Alex-
Continued on Page E-10, Col. 1</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn82015313/1932-05-25/ed-1/seq-2</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>McNamara. Labor Leader, to Learn
Federal Term Friday.
John J. McNamara of near Fort
ville, former labor leader who served
a prison term in connection with
the Los Angeles Times bombing,
probably will be sentenced in fed
eral court Friday on a charge of
possessing a still.
McNamara was convicted by a
jury on a liquor charge indictment
several weeks ago. but has not been
sentenced. He has indicated his in
tention to cock an appeal.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86063730/1934-05-03/ed-1/seq-10</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Clarence Darrow. most famous
criminal lawyer in the United
States, may close his colorful
legal career by defending Samuel
insult, former utilities magnate,
who soon will go on trial in Chi
cago facing charges of embezzle
ment. larceny and using the mails
to defraud as a result of the col
lapse of his J3.000.000.000 utili
ties empire Champion of the
“under dog" throughout his life,
Darrow. a fellow Chicagoan, is
reported to be seriously consider
ing going to Insull’s defense, al
though he is in virtual retirement
now at the age of 77 Darrow
gained world-wide attention
through hi* defense or tne Mc
Namara brothers, convicted of
bombing the Los Angeles Times
building in 1911. his defense of
Locb and Leopold, serving life
terms for the murder of Bobby
Franks, his defense of John T
Scopes in Tennessee's celebrated
theory of evolution case in 192S;
and ms oei* nac oi nn. uranvn
Fortewuc, her son-in-law. Lhu
Thoma Ma..sic and two Amcrict
seamen, convicted and then ir
mediately pardoned for the mu
der of an Hawaiian, one of mix a,
cused of attacking Mrs. Thal^
Ma •sic and many other equally f
mourn lejral cases.
Extortion Plot
Called a Prank
.. .,.-_f</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-ouija-board</id>
    <results>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88084272/1910-10-01/ed-1/?sp=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>THE NEW TALKING BOARD.
Tfce
MjitarlMS AaBaaeaaeat Which la
raeelaattBt; Okls reettltk
Many of our readers will still remember
planchette, the strange little heart-shaped
board with a pencil at its point which used
to walk over yards of paper and write no and
of tenie and nonsense if the finger tips of two
persons touched the upper surface of the
board.
Planchetts had Ka day, and mostl died
out But the same mysterious force which
used to impel it it moving now another kind
of little board, and setting whole eommuni
Uet of eminently sober and respectable Ohio
people on their heads.
You see how it it made. A bit of board,
say 18x30 inches, is lettered, rather large,
with the alphabet, A, B, C, D, etc The
letters are put a small distance apart At
the upper corners of the board are written
the words "yes" and "no," the "yes" on tha
left, the "no" oa the right On tha left and
right hand lower corners respectively are
written "good evening and "good night
Underneath tha letters of the alphabet are
the figures in a row, the whole arranged like
thit:
t'esV no.
j ABC OS VGH I JKL MIf
ibPQBSTUVrVXVK.,
1334T8V0 i
Good-eve.
Good-night
Hen a tiny table it made with four legs.
It is three or four inches high and very thin
and light Two persons tit opposite each
other and take the board upon their knees at
in the picture. The little four-legged table ia
placed upon the board. The two persons
grasp tightly with the thumb and forefinger
the comers of the table that are next to them.
TBS TAXKXJfQ fJOABDb
The two sit down and become quiet, asking
rtioml" After a few minutes the little table
begins to move over the board, It is an In
tel lig nt, or at least, a semi-intelligent force
that guides the table, for it answers
questions. Bomettmes It talks utter nonsense
and again it will write real information.
The table spells out sentences in this way.
When a question is asked, the table moves
towards the tetters, and the foot stops upon
the first one of the sentence to be written out
Then it passes to the next one and the next
and so on, with more or less rapidity, a
gentleman, who hat experimented with the
thing, says: "Sometime the table will cover
two letters with Its feet and then yon hang
on and ask that the foot be moved from the
wrong letter, which will be done,"
One man who tnougnt nit lamiiy was
spending too much time over the talking ma
chine burned it up. Then he left noma on a
Journey. When the talking board could not
be found some one made anotner, ana tne
amusement went on. as before. To tho qu
tion what had become of the other board the
answer was given, "Jack burned It up,
which somewhat astonished Jack on his re
turn.
The questions may be asked mentally, even
by persons sitting in the room several feet
away from the operators, and tha answers
are given Just as readily. Ia some cases re
markable and truthful revelations are said to
have been given about living persons. But it
it not well to girt too much heed to these
revelations.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82016373/1890-12-21/ed-1/?sp=2</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Nineteenth Century
This most interesting and
mysterious talking board has
awakened great curiosity wher
ever shown.
It surpasses in its results
second sight, mind reading, or
clairvoyance.
It consists of a small table
placed upon a large board con
taining the alphabet and nume
rals. By simply resting the
fingers of two persons upon
the small table it moves, and
to all intents and purposes be
comes a living, sensible thing,
giving intelligent answer to
any questions that can be pro
pounded. Wonderful as this may seem
the "OUIJA" was thoroughly
tested at the United States
Patent Office before the patent
was allowed.
For sale by all first-class toy
dealers and stationers.
MANUFACTURED BY
THE KEMARD NOVELTY m,
220 SOUTH CHARLES ST.,
BALTIMORE, MD.
de21-lt,'i
</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn94052989/1893-11-14/ed-1/?sp=8</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>WEIRD WRITINGS.
The Planchette Craze Has
Broken Out Again.
UNSEEN FORCES AT WORK.
Some Uncanny Pranks of a Little
Instrument That Once Held the
Attention of the World.
There Is a planchette fever in San Fran
cisco.
Clubs of patient sitters, anxious to hold
communion with the dead and distant liv
ing, have been formed here and in Oak
land. Daily and nightly seances are being
held.
Plancbette is old, so old that it is almost
new again. Early in the fifties the weird
little contrivance was invented and ten
years later nearly the whole civilized world
was teaming with a recital of its wonders.
The most uncanny tales were related of
the marvelous doings of the instrument,
and for a time the greatest scientific minds
of the world were interested iv its queer
pranks. Such men as Tyndall and Faraday
were drawn Into controversies pro and con
over the merits of this occult agency.
Exhaustive essays were written and
learned lectures delivered to prove that
planchette was a fraud and to prove that
planchette's powers were supernatural.
But it all ended where it began. The
deepest study and the most careful analy
sis of the wiles and ways of planchette
developed nothing of scientific value either
to the student of the occult or the natural
forces.
And so the planchette fever died as
quickly as it had grown. Men and women
went back to their workaday world or con
tinued their occult studies unuer different
auspices. Planchette had it« little day nnd
then died a natural death. Or, if it did not
i die entirely, it lapsed into a slate of coma
j from whicn it is only now being resur-
I rected. To-day, in San Fraucisco aud in
j Oakland, and perhaps In other parts of
ihe world, great numbers of men and
women are bent on solving the mysteries
i that still cling to this little contrivance.
And it is all because of that irrepressible
j desire of man to penetrate the mysteries
j of the future. f ,v
What does to-morrow hold for me.
That is the question nearest the heart of
most men to-day. lt is a very part of the
commercial spirit of the age. And as yet
science has made no advances toward
placing the means within reach of answer
ing it. So planchette comes again to fill
the gap between the known and the un
known.
What started the fever no one seems to
i know. 'Hint it has been started and has
already interested hundreds of intelligent
men and women no one doubts, for the evi
dence is clear.
You know what planchette is, do you
j not, and how it operates? Some have
thought there was a hidden secret in its
I construction, but this is wrong. Never
was a wonderful device more simply con
trived; There is first a heart-shaped cedar
board. Pendant from the points of the
angle are little legs with metal or wooden
castors. At the end of the board is an
aperture for the insertion of a lead pencil.
Those who fit to planchette for communi
cations from this world or the next place
a baud each on the surface of the board,
then wait till the "spirit moves." And
the spirit has been moving pretty rapidly
in these parts of the world for the last
few nights. Dire things have been fore
told and timely warnings given.
Ordinarily planchette will write out
what it has to say if time be given i\ but
the quicker way is to write the alphabet
and the simple negative and affirmative on
a large sheet of white paper and let plan
chette spell out its messages by pointing to
tbe letters.
It was this method pursued py a party
of well-known clubmen who began as
i skeptics Friday evening and went home at
I daybreak firmly convinced that there were
i at least many things that they had little
j dreamed of In their phiiosophy. Only two
members of the party placed tbeir hands
on the instrument at one time. The others
j looked on and scoffed.
"We were all unbelievers when we sat
down to that table," said the member of
the party who told the story to a Call
man yesterday. "For a while planchetie
refused to move and we were almost on
the point of giving it up for the night,
when, without un Instant warning, the in
strument gave a sudden jerk and almost
flew from uuder the fingers of Jones and
Smith.
"Roth the men turned pale at this and
in order to rally themselves they accused
each other of having moved the planchette.
On their honor both men denied this, but
since neither had believed his own accusa
tion the denials were useless.
"I think it was a wife or a sister of
Jones that came first. I bave forgotten
the name of the spirit or influence, or
whatever it was, that purported to move
the instrument, but the information it im
parted can be easily verified or disproved
when the next news from Samoa arrives.
"It spelled out 'Apia' first, very clearly
and unhesitatingly. Then it went on to
say that a terrible hurricane would sweep
over the Samoan Islands on the 10th of
November and that two vessels would be
lost In the storm. And touching this
event it would say no more, though we
plied it with queries for a long time.
"Another influence came. I remember
tbe name, but shall not give it.
'Dead or living?' asked Smith.
'Living,' came the answer, but Smith
knew this already, for the name it gave
was the name of his sweetheart.
'What have you to tell me?' queried
Smith, and then he wished he had not,
for the answer that came distressed bim
sorely.
"Twill not marry you,' it spelled out
with painful accuracy.
'Why not?', was the natural question
that followed when Smith had recovered
his presence of mind and bad determined
to face it out.
'Because I like D— letter,' came the
answer.
"Then two men glared at each other for
a moment, for D— sat at the opposite end
of the table waiting bis turn to try plan
chette.^^StHß^^B^o96iQH''SK^
"Now, if It were not already notorious
that D— hail been a little soft on Smith's
sweetheart of late we would have passed
over this little incident as one of the
vagaries of plancbette. But Smith couldn't
take it in this light. He was crushed, and
Invited D— to take his place. 1 needn't
tell you that D— declined the invitation,
but I would stake a small sum that" D—
has his bands on a plancbette this moment.
a,\*'l look Smith's place at the planchette
and presently the' thing began ;to move
again. This time it discarded the use of
the alphabet and gave its message in writ
ing.
"Now, I am not going to place any reli
ance on this thing till I see how it turns
out, but the message that came to me is
Important if it is true.
'"I am an enemy,' it wrote.
'"Are you going to thrash him?' asked
Jone?, who likes to be facetious when
there is the least call for it.
."'No!' said planchette. Then after a
pause it carefully wrote out, '1 am going
to harm him. He is my enemy and I will
be revenged.'
"Well, all this meant nothing without a
name, and no name had been given yet.
Again I asked for the name and ■it not
only wrote oat the name of tbe man who
happens to be smarting under a very just
punishment that i Inflicted upon, him, but
wrote it in bis own handwriting. a
''You should have seen some of the faces
of the men who sal about that table when
they recognized the handwriting. One of
the men who bad laughed loudest and
scoffed the most when we first sat down
found it necessary to go outside for fresh
air." There was no more laughter tbat
evening. i
"Then it came into my bead to ask plan
chette something about itself, but before
we put the questions both Jones and my
self were blindfolded. This precaution is
unnecessary, for it is simply impossible to
move planchette as it does move without
exerting a physical force that would be
readily detected. However, we did this
more to convince ourselves than others.
".'Are you inspired?' asked.
"'Yes,' came the answer.
'By a good power?'
"The instrument fairly flew to the word
'no.'
'By the devil said Jones.
'The devil,' it spelled out without the
least hesitation. s:
'Who are you?' I inquired.
'An agent of the devil,' replied plan
chetie, and this time in writing.
"And after that there was not a man in
the room brave enough to put bis hand on
that instrument."
The above questions and answers can
be vouched for by -more than one man
whose word in the commercial world is as
good as his bond, and many similar dia
logues might be cited to prove— prove
well, to prove that plancbette has a strong
hold on the people of this city once more.
Whether the craze will die out before it
reaches any great proportions again re
mains to be seen.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85058396/1915-12-11/ed-1/?sp=17</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
Tho oulja board Is coming back
tnto favor and has been taken up
I quit extensively by society women
v In New York, Boston, Chicago, St.
Louis and various parts of the coun
try. Perhaps tho most remarkable le-
Iccnt experiences with it arc those of
Mrs, John Curran of St, Louis. Sho
has been in communication, she says,
with the spirit of Patience Worth, a
woman beliovcd to have existed in
lhe Colonial days and who not only
has sent philosophical axioms that
are characteristic of tho Puritans
but even has gone to tho extent of
sending outlines of plays and es
says and has gone extensively Into
the dictation of poetry. More than
300,000 words havo been received
from this supposed spirit in ihieo
years.
Patience Worth talks In a strange
t English that is archaic and not
J 1 found in the best authors and yet
j may have at one time been the
tongue of Inhabitants of this coun
try. Long condemned by religious as
the direct agency of satan and by
i skeptics as the toy of the supcrsti-
tlous, the ouija board is being ro
f stored to its own former popularity
I through the curiosity of society wo
men. In many parts of the country oo
clety women are devoting their timo
to "communicating" with spirits in
tho other world.
Many sti'ango results of such com
munications are reported and a ao
t clety woman is unhappy indeed if
she hasn't at least one good spirit
i in tho world of mystery who is al
B) ways ready to send a message at her
m, control's pleasure.
Ill Even in staid St. Louis where so-
lit! cIety women arc supposed to bo
1$ very conservative, tho ouija board
il has been, restored to favor whilo
HA
in New York and In various
cities of the east it is quite the
"rage."
In St Louis Mrs. John H. Curran
has gotten into touch with one Pa
tience Worth of Spiritland and has
transcribed more than 300,000 words
thiough the ouija board, all of which
will be published at some future
date.
Patience Worth is believed from
her peculiar choice of words and
phraseology to be a Colonial dame,
who has been wandering about In
space for a long time, burning to
send her messages back to the mun
dane sphere yet finding no source of
communication until Mrs. Curran
bought a ouija board and com
menced taking messages.
THROUGH
CURIOSITY.
The board Avas purchased through
curiosity. There is something fas
cinating about the tales told of tho
little board, whether they be- true
or false. It is known that a num
ber of people have asked the board
to tell them in what land their dead
iclativcs liugercd and were shocked
considerable- when the naughty Utile
hoard spelled out a word starling
A ith an H and ending with an L.
Many have thought that the words
written bv the board were the result
of the mental influences oC the per
son opeiating it. while others have
credited it with supernatural pow
ers. In tho use of tho board at the Cur
ran home, Mrs. Curran always is one
of two whose "hands are on the
board. The latter is arranged on
two wheels and has a pencil at the
end. As the vibration of the fingers
of tho holders develops the pencil
moves over a sheet of paper and
prints numerals o'r letters of the al
phabet, While Mrs. Curran operates tho
board her husband transcribes tho
message as sho reads it to him.
The "Patience Worth" matter be
gan to be transcribed in June, 1913.
Since that time Mrs. Curran has
made public as the products of Pa
tience Worth a six-act play entitled
"Red Wing." a novel called "Tclka"
and numerous verses, essays and
bits of philosiphy.
The quaint language of these writ
ings has probably attracted more at
tention than their literary merit, tho
latter being a matter of some dis
cussion. They are in an antique
language, not the English of Chau
cer, Spenser or any other well-
known classic English writer, but
possibly more like the common
speech of the English people of an
early day.
It is known to travelers that an
antique, almost archaic, form of
English still Is spoken in remote
communities of England. Theie are
districts of England whose inhabi
tants have great difficulty in under
standing or in making themselves
understood by the coster-cockney
class.
Mrs. Curran, however, says sho
has no personal acquaintance with
such speech and that she has not
gone farther in her study of classic
English than other well read per
sons. The language used' by Patience
Worth, she explains, is as strange
to her as It is to others.
Mrs. Curran recently gave to the
Fapyrus Club of St. Louis some of
her messages from Patience Worth,
one of them being a special messago
that Patience had sent the club. It
read:
PATIENCE WORTH'S
MESSAGE.
Good Dames and SIrrahs At the
board thou hast sat and cat of
earth's grow. Aye, and now do ye
cat o' the grow thou knowest not the
looting place of. Yea, thou shalt
hark unto the woid o' MEN, and jet
they do to prate o' DAME. Ayca,
and methlnks 'tis a word aspoke'
amany, that be not the word that
hid 'pon the lung, lest the Dame be
offended I
Aye, then come thou and ait 'bout
the board, and thine cars shall hark
tmto the words o' me, and thou shalt
sec the cloth o' me the hands o' the
loves o' mc did to fashion out for
me. Ayea, I then shall sit me meek,
and thread mc up a bobbins full for
the next o' put.
Ayca, and 'tis frocked that I shall
to be, and nay dame shall see!
Awoe! Nay, this be a piddlc-put-tlng,
good folk!
Athin (within) thy heart shall set
the me o' me at thy go ahence. And
'tis nhope I be 'tis a loving wampth
'twill find. And so dost thou to
smile, 'tis Bweets and love 1 cast
thee. And doth thy heart to shut it
up, lo, then shall I to knock till thou
dost leave me in.
A night o' cheer. A heart o' love!
A God's wish o' loving 'pon thy day.
Anight! Anight!
HOW IT
BEGAN.
Mrs. Curran told her audience of
her first experiences with tho ouija
WW
w
board and of the puzzling messages
received. Later sho used the'board
together with Mrs Emily Grant
Hutchings and began to receive
sentences which foimcd maxims and
philosophical paragrapbs. Then
came the announcement:
"Many moons ago I lived. Patience
Worth, my namo. If thou shalt live
then so shall I. I make my bread by
thy hearth"
The word "bread." Mrs. Currau
later learned, lefeired to the literary
products embodied in the messages.
Mrs. Curran said she would not at
tempt to say whelhcr Patience
Worth was a spirit, but spoko of ,ber
as a beautiful personality, which had
come to seem not a mystery but a
fellowship.
She said the messages came to her
in daylight as well as at night and
that there is no trance connected
with them.
"The words come in sort o a
rhythm," Mrs. Curran explained,
"and I record just what comes
whether I understand it or not."
Pnticuce has been tested by rnoro
than 200 persons and her messages
have never varied. A professor from
the University of Indiana visltod
Mrs. Cunan to investigate her com
munication with Patience Worth.
William Marion' Reedy, editor of
the Mirror, and Caspar Yost, editor
of a SL Louis newspaper, became ac
quainted with Patience Worth and
both declaic her genuine. Yost has
described her as a "spinster of un
certain age; a writer, but a poet by
preference. White the average spirit
stalks dismal and wailing lugubri
ously through the flnito world, Pa
tience comes with a laugh, Yost said.
She remarks. ''I be no sorrj' singer,"
and proves it by many witticisms.
EDITOR
DESCRIBES HER.
Reedy calls Patience's doctrines
Pantelstic.
He describes her as follows: "She
fs a little woman, dressed In gtaj;
with a little bonnet, ribbons coming
down and tied under her chin. There
are lines in her face, not the re
written wrinkles of the smiles or
her youth, but the results of ex
perience Her eyes are biown liico
autumn leaves after a rain. She Is
-between 45 and 50 years old, spright
ly, dainty, delicate.
"Sho has stood beside the stock
ade helping a good man load a gun,
while he defends the settlement
against the savage horde of In
dians." Reedy said the theory was ad
vanced that she was filled in an In
dian massacre and this question was
askcu of her. Sho intimated that
something of this sort had happened
to her and she was asked if she had
not been taken captive oy the In
dians. "Nay, something worse," was her
reply.
'.'She speaks an English almost
pure and undefiled," Reedy said of
her "There is an absence from it
of all the derivatives of France and
Rome, and sho rarely uses a word
of more than two syllables. Her an
swers are- diredt and almost invari
ably in parables. She has respect
for her interlocutor's intelligence."
Reedy said sho is not another
Sappho, or George Elliott, or Mrs.
Humphrey ward nor a Sara Teas
dale,' but rather echoes of all of thct
poets. He said theie runs a consist
ent character through her works and
in two years she has not gotten "out
of chaiactcr." Sho never has used a
modern word or expression and he
illustrated the seeming significance
of this by pointing out how difficult
it would be for a man trained In
Irish or negro dialect to make a 30
minute talk without breaking out of
the character.
"She has nothing lo tell, in my
opinion, "Reedy said, "but she com
mands my admiration and reverence.
She tells nothing- that we have not
heard from tho old masters and
bards."
"What of the divinity of Christ?"
Kcody at one time asked her through
the ouijd board. She answered, "He
bought thee of his loving."
"What of love?" he asked. "Tho
love there is but tho o'er drip of lovo
here" came the respou&c of tho
board.
"Describe tho place where you
are?" sho was asked. "Think you
"Patience Worth," Mythical
Character, Startles Literary
World With Her Quaint I
English In Essays, Plays and H
Novels Noted Writers Are H
Puzzled Over the Output of H
This Woman Supposed to H
Have i Lived 300 Years Ago H
there Is bottom or top; this is a
walless country."
"Can you do anything you want
over there 7" The answer was:
"When you put the will you put the
limit."
"Put" in Patience's vocabulary re
sponds to the modern verb "to do."
"Patience may be a second person
ality of Mrs. Curran," -Reedy sato.
"but she teaches a lovo that is
greater than we can conceive and
that death is the keeper of unknown
redemption."
LITTLE COLONIAL
DAME.
Mrs. Emily Hutchings, who -was
one of the first to receive 'with Mrs.
Curran the messages from Patlenco
Worth, said the first glimmering or
the quaint personality of the little
Colonial dame came in the maxim:
"A busy saw gathereth no rust."
One of the sentiments expressed
by Patience Worth is: "A blighted
bud may hold a sweeter message
than the lovllest flower; for God
hath kissed her wounded heart and
left a promise there."
Of the seances, Mrs. Curran says:
"I sit with a friend, our hands up
on the board, which I havo come to
believe is nothing more than a con
centrator. There is no trance. Ev
erything is quiet with the exception
of Patience Worth. The only
definite part is that while I put my
thoughts awhither, as Patience
would Bay, and immediately the sto
ries, poems, plays., parables, or
whatever her work for the sitting IH
may be, is shown to mo in tiny pic- JH
lures, beautiful and distinct a3 IH
though my eyes saw them.
"The characters move and speak H
and my hands fly over the letters jH
much too fast for me to anticipate- H
even one word. J
"I cannot account for the langu- jH
age. The words seem to be spoken ilH
to me. though I cannot 'say 1 hear llH
them In the sense that we hear tho iH
voice that speaks aloud to us. The H
words come m sort of a rhythm. I lH
am not familiar with old Euglish jH
and yet even the conversations -are H
in this archaic tongue." jH
Psychologists recently havetakcn ,H
up a" study of Mrs. Curran and tho M
Mvstcrlous Patience Worth. Some jM
believe that Paticnco Worth is Mrs. jH
Curran's sub-conscious self. Others jH
have departed in doubt and without jH
expressing an opinion. iH
The ouija board has been con- JH
demned by various religious bodies, iH
but society is taking it up beside il
these prohibitions. The Catholic tl
church has condemned it as a super-
stitlous practice. H
Other religious bodies havo u- H
clarcd that the devil is in hc boaid H
and employs it to send his messages. H
Whatever the truth may be, so-
ciety has gone into the mystery of lH
tho board, not so much with the ob- iH
jeet of definitely deciding if it really jH
is the medium of communication H
with the other world but to,gratlfy H
society's chief attribute Curiosity. H
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1915-12-12/ed-1/?sp=33</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn96076839/1920-06-25/ed-1/?sp=3</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>WHO INVENTED OUIJA
Brothers Ask Baltimore Court to
Settle Dispute.
Brothers, Apparently Lacking Falfh
In Talking Board, Ask Judge
to Decide.
Baltimore. At the moment that the
oulja board, which some years ago ex-
cited the country and then virtually
disappeared, has again come Into the
Umellgbt throughout the world, two
brothers are engaged In litigation here
over the ownership of the patent, t
The trial Is now In progress of the
suit of Isaac Fuld, trading as the
Southern Toy company, who I ask
ing for an Injunction to restrain his
brother, William Fuld, from deriving
pecuniary profits through the sale of
the oulja board.
The plaintiff asserts that In 1904 he
originated, manufactured and placed
upon the market the board under the
copyright name of the oracle 'and
that later William Fuld started the
manufacture of ihe oulja board.
William Fuld asserts that he and
Isaac Fuld were In business together
years ago, and that the oulja board
Is the original talking board, and
claims that tlie oracle talking board
manufactured by Isaac Fuld Is a
copy of the one placed on the market
by him.
The Fulds about 28 years ago were
In charge of a wooden toy factory
known as the Kennard Manufacturing
company, and the oulja board was one
of the devicesthey made to entertain
the young. It quickly won tremen
dous popularity nnd so overshadowed
the business of tho concern that the
plant was largely devoted to the mak
ing of. the oulja board.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1920-01-25/ed-1/?sp=32</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>The B?by M tiBeiig Raised bu
4
C
World for tne Daily Guidance of Littl
Wortn Wee Explained by Mrs. John Cu
Says She Was Commanded ty a Spir
Fortn, Find a Certain Infant and A
Spectral Messages from tke Qtner
EvTUL Y -public Ubrary and aU Um book stores hay?
on thiTalr shelves one or more novels by ''Pattereoe
Worth.'' But th?-? is do such living humau be
ioff aa "Patience Worth "?abe is a spook, a spirit, s
ghost, a voice from the world beyond the grave It 1?
daini-ed
These entertaining and ravther well written novels
War? dictated by the spirit of "Patience Worth" to
Mrs. John Curran, of St. Louis, Mra. Curran solemn
ly Ms?trta. Mrs. Curran says aha wrote every word of
that? novels and many poem* on a ouija board word
fttr word as the spectral voice of "Patience Worth"
whiipered them in her ear. t
shit theae spooky novel? ?ire not what this page
deals with to-*lay. ?A nor? oaereet?ng thing to being
done by this spook, .vccortllng to Mra. Curran and
her friends. 'Patience Worth" oommividtTsd Mra.
Curran, who ia childless, to seSarch for a certain rad
head*id, blue eyed infant "with dark linea in than."
whoee father was English and mother waa Scsotoh.
Such a baby waa found and adopted by Mra.
Curran
And thia child, embodying to-day features and
parentage similar to "Patience Worth," who tited 200
years ago, is being brought up by ita spectral god
mother Day by day "Patience Worth" gives Mra.
Curran an ouija board message of advice about little
Patienoe Worth Wee whenever il to U4>?*mI4mL
Three-year-old Patience
Worth Wee, iron* re
cent photograph of tho
ghost-guided lituo ono
ia Forest Park, St.
Louis, She is wearing
tho clothing ordered by
hot "spirit mother."
SIX years ago Mrs. John H Curran, of St. Louis, a
peculiarly healthy-minded, normal young woman,
who is the wife of the former Immigration Commis
sioner of Misitvouri, began for amusement to experiment
with the ouija board. This peculiar instrument for receiv
ing meaaages foom the beyond" consists of a flat wooden
board, about two feet long by one and a half wide, on
which are th? letters of the alphabet, the numerala up to
ten and the words ''Yea," "Mo," "Don't know" and
"Good-by." A little heart-shaped table on three legs is
placed on top of the board. The sitters place the board
upon their knees, the finger tips of both hands lightly upon
the heart-shaped table. After a while an "influence,"
"apirit" or "spook" begins to move the heart-shaped
board, whose narrow end then points to the letters, spell
ing out the words of ?ta* message. A third person, an
observer, acts as amenuensis, taking down the letters as
the pointer indicates them.
The "mestages" are accounted for by non-spiritualista
as an expression of the sub-conscious self of one or both
of the sitters; the mysterious movement of the table is
supposed to be due to unconscious muscle rhythms of the
hands of the sitters.
Whatever the explanation, Mrs. Curran began to hear
from someone who signed herself "Patience Worth" and
who spelled out upon the board sentences in remarkable
English?archaic, a forgotten dialect. This ghostly per
sonage speedily developed into the strongest kind of a
personality. She had been, she wrote, a maiden of Dor
setshire. England, who lived about 1650. She was a
weaver's daughter, an only child. She wrote that "my
thumb is thick from twisting flax" and speaks of deliver
ing fine linen to the "castle folk." Her father left to
come to America, and after the death of her mother.
Patience says she followed him to the new world. ?She
was then thirty-five. Her new home was in the vicinity
of Martha's Vineyard and Nantucket. Near there she
tv a? buried, and now, she says, "a tree grows out of my
grave."
Soon she began to dictate stories and poems with ex
traordinary rapidity and facility. The first book pub
lished was "Patience Worth." The "Sorry Tale," a
story based on the episode of the impenitent thief on Ihe
cross, came out in 1916 and "Hope Trueblood." the last
book, was a story of old England.
The remarkable literary excellence of these writings
attracted widespread attention. Their dialect
passed every teat of experts. It was proven that
Mrs. Curran had no previous knowledge of them,
nor had she the education displayed by the com
munications. Dr. Martin F. Prince, the famous
neurologist, diagnosed Patience "asa sub-conscious
personality of Mrs. Curran and offered to rid her of it
by hypnotism. Mrs. Curran refused to have "Patience"
banished by this means or any other, and scoffs at the
sub conscious theory. Other distinguished scientists
studied her case, but with no better results.
For three years the "ghost" of Patience Worth?or
whatever it is that responda to that nam?2?had been dic
tating to Mrs. Curran by means of the oirija board as a
concentrator. One book had been printed, another waa
on the way to the printer. The first book was already
promising an excellent sale. Reviews had been flattering
and the publie was becoming interested
Then one evening, after the Currans had been' dis
cussing this materialistically agreeable result of the.man
ifestations, Patience Worth exploded a bombshell. In
the quaint old English words which she uses she an
nounced that inasmuch an there "seemed to be some
money in sight." and since it did not belong to the Cur
rans. "but to God," that they should seek "a wee babe
that had nothing, nothing and take it and care for iti"
This was. indeed, disconcerting. The Curran house
was a well-filled one. There was a grandfather, a mother
in-law, a stepdaughter and the husband and wife. Be
sides, they had counted upon using the money for thorn
selves.
Patience, however, was determined and explicit. Sho
caustically called attention to the fact that the emolu
menta of her bock did not belong to those who simply
took down her dictation, but that as the author and main
spring of the volume the returns from it were hers to do
with aa she Dleased.
"I am a weaver of cloth," said Patience on that night,
in the curious imagery she loves to use, "and this cloth
weave is not for him who hath. Thou ehalt seek a wee
one who hath naught, and thou shalt deliver the goods
of me unto it? hands, and ye shalt speak ita name
?Patience Worth."*
This was an order, not a request 1 And to it when the
first shock of surprise had worn off the Currans gladly
bowed.
??L?ook ye.'' the '^heat** went on, "this shall be one
who is sorely in need, mind ye Ye ?hall whisper sweets
unto it. even unto the wee ear that knoweth not thy
words, and tell unto it of a fairy dame who shall minister
unto it and of Him who sent her And she shell be the
love of all who love me and shall smile sweeta unto
them.*'
"But why a girl instead of a boyt" the Currans aaked
anxiously.
"Ye aee,'* answered Patience cryptically enough, "a
man laddie hath man'? cunning, but the wee dame??ah,
I know I"
The Curran? quite naturally asked about the parent
age of the child, ita legitimacy and many other important
things, not the least of which was a description of it so
that they might know when they bad found tbe babe
Patience had in mind
She gave them certain directions???rather vague; told
them "not to mind earth's law but God's"?referring
unquestionably to the matter of parentage and to watch
close if there were any blood taints, but not to go back
further than the grandparent?.. She wanted the child
dressed simply, she concluded, and asked thai "about its
neck thou ?halt hang a sign of Him." The Curran?, and
rightly it, turned out later, construed this to mean
cross."
"Ye shall be upon tbe path! E'en now the wee one
is waiting," she urged.
So the hunt began for a child who wouid answer the
description. The entire "Patience Worth" clan was sent
out on the seareh. Two physicians were selected to ex
amine it when found for blood taint! Much ground wa?
covered in the next month. There were handicaps?an
interesting one the refusal by a certain large St. Louis
foundling institution to allow any baby to be taken from
there because "Mrs. Curran wrote on a ouija board."
During this search "Patience," who seems to have a
strange sense of humor at times, remained silent. Then
one night, according to Mrs. Curran, she directed them
to cease, telling them there was no use in looking for
"one that was not whole," and that in due time certain
signs would be given them whereby they would know
what to do adding that if they did continue it would be
"like a wolf seeking for a fat fowl to feed well upon
when the bird was still in the egg." After this, other
weeks passed by without any reference being made by
"Patience Worth" to the matter.
Then one morning Mrs. Curran met an old friend
whom she had not seen for years, and in the course of a
ride together told some of the details of the quest for the
baby. The friend, in return, told of a young wife who
was about to become a mother, who was practically home
less and friendless, and whose husband had been killed
some time before in a mill accident. That night g mes
sage from "Patience Worth" indicated that at last the
Curraros were on the right track and that which she had
prophesied M'as about to occur.
The next day Mrs. Curran went to see this woman,
who was very ill. A fever of preparation began imme
diately. Layette cradle, perambulator, lawyers, adoption
papers?everything was made ready just as though the
thing were already settled. Seemingly the possibility
that the expected child might be a boy was never for a
moment considered.
The mother-to-be signed the adoption papers, but held
them under the agreement that if she lived she was to
keep the expected child, but that if she died, then the
Currans were to have the baby.
Six weeks later, as Mrs Curran was writing with
"Patience" upon the now well-known "Sorry Tale," the
"ghost" stopped the dictation at exactly nine o'clock.
"This be enough," she wrote, and the board became
quiet.
Everyone was on tip-toe with expectation. It had
been arranged that they should be called by phone at ten
o'clock for news of the birth, which had been imminent
for some hours.
On the hour the telephone rang and word came that a
girl child had been, bom at exactly the moment when
"Patience" had stopped the writing
When the child was seen it had all the marks that
were expected. Its hair was red as "Patience Worth"
had described her own. It had blue eyes with dark lines
in them, like those which -"Patience" had said she pos
sessed when on earth. Its parentage was the same as
"Patience," whose father, she had said, was English and
whose mother was Scotch.
The baby's mother died four days later and the child
was legally adopted by the Currans acting for "Patience
Worth She was christened as Patience Worth Wee
Curran on November 26, 1916, the Rev George Wales
King, a prominent St. Louis minister, officiatine?. Mrs.
Cha?es H. McKee, an equally well-known social leader,
is her godmother, and Casper S. Yost, editor of one of St.
Louis' leading newspapers, is her godfather, with Dr
and Mrs Major E. Woodruff her sponsors.
The "ghost" having thus picked out her child, having
watched over its entrance into this world, having given
all essential directions for its discovery, was it not to be
expected that she would now take a most active part, just
like any real flesh-and-blood mother in bringing it upt
"Patience" soon answered this qnestioft in no un
certain way. It was clear that she intended to have a
finger in every detail?clothing, feeding, education, piny
and all elements of the child's life. And here must be
raised the interesting question of jnst what relationship
"Patience Worth" elsims to tittle Patience Worth Wee
?Curran. Does she assume to be its actual mot her t
Even admitting that there is such a disembodied
entity as "Patience Worth," what possible physical in
fluence could a "ghtMt" of a woman dead, on her own
account, almost three hundred year? have nr`on the
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86063381/1920-02-24/ed-1/?sp=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>REVELATION OF OUIJA
FORMS BASIS OF LAW SUIT
Lockport, 111., Feb. 24.An Ouija
board and its uncanny revelations
form the basis of a $10,000 suit here
against Albert Yost. Recently Yost's
home was burglarized. An Ouija
board was consulted to solve the mys
tery surrounding the robbery. Answ
ering the question "Who robbed my
house?" the board is said to have
replied "Frank Walter." Walter is
Yost's neighbor. They have been
lifelong friends. The board is also
said to have implicated Mrs. Walter.
The board's accusations became
known to Mrs. Walter, who called at
the Yost home. She was told the
Yosts had nothing to retract and
forthwith filed suit for $10,000
against Yosts, alleged slander. The
Yosts deny the charge and insist they
have uttered no word which might be
interpreted as defaming the charac
ter of the Walters.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1920-11-14/ed-1/?sp=70</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Ouija Board Invades Britain
LONDON, Nov. 10.
THE ouija board has invaded
Britain! It masquerades un?
der the pseudonym of "plan?
chette," but it is the familiar
alphabet and flatiron device that has
helped to while away the tedium of
prohibition in the United States.
And apparently it has landed in
force, because even now officials of
women's clubs are debating as to
whether the planchette is a game,
or, if it isn't, what it is.
"If it is a game." argued one club
secretary, "it should be played as a
game In the cardroom and during
the regulation card hours. As it is,
the planchette enthusiasts are busily
occupied with their favorite pastime
from early morn to dewy eve."
Although she waxed poetic at the
end, it was evident that the official
was really disturbed about the exact
status of the planchette. F-r it is
said that the fascinating business of
receiving messages from the spin*
world?not the s?ance which was w
popular following the war, but the
more informal question-and-answer
of the ouija board?is quite ousting
the card games.
If no regulation planchette is at
hand a substitute, consisting of ?B
ordinary inverted tumbler surround?
ed by cardboard letters, is CtB*
into play. The fingers are pl??*11
upon the bottom of this glass, j^*
as they are upon the little triant"
lar device of the real ouija boaru.
and it skips lightly from one letf*r
to another spelling out its message*.
And the planchette is less ex?
pensive than bridge, because no on*
yet has thought of betting on tM
spirits!
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1921-10-26/ed-1/?sp=22</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>18 the 0uga Rosn MA8
Mental Trounble i
Washington?
By BILL PRICE.
Whether there is truth in a statmmnt that the ouija
board is adding patients to Wasinta asums
through disturbing infinenoes augon District mentalitin,
students of mental phenomena will be inteAsted in the
fact that the board takes its name from the French
word oui (yes) and the German word ja (yes). Its
origin is somewhat obscure. Both the planohette and
ouija, somewhat simila in appearanes, date back to
about 1855, and for a while were objects of consider
able superstition. The planchette is a small board
fitted with a pencil and two casters, made to move
easily over a sheet of paper when the hands rest lightly
on it. The dictionary says the ouija "is a form of
planchatte used in spiritualistic seaness or the like.
It consists of two parts, a board containing the al
phabet and other characters, and a planehette, with
a pointer substituted for the pencil."
Investigation of automatic writings fail to find that
the two boards have any origin in the mysticisms of
Egypt. One writer is of the opinion that the iret at
tempt in ouijaing was made by a man on his wife's
breadboard. The skeptical refer to the board as
wholly a modem trick afair which has no connection
with Eastern or other metaphysics.
Some of the noted spiritualists of the world make use
of the ouija or planchette and carefully study the
results. An able group of psychologists regard the
ouija as a dangerous deception. Their theory is that
the subconscious mind of the operator directs the
fingers in such a way as to convey the information
hoped for. The operator, they hold, is as innocent of
this subconscious process as a sleep-walker is of what,
he is doing, and naturally puts a supernatural con
struction on the outcome.
Leading spiritualists and other believers in higher
agencies than natural ones, confident that communica
tion with the other world is not only established but
is developing into an understanding that will glorify
humanity, are willing to accept the ouija board or any
other method of transmission that will add ti the in
formation they feel they now possess. Those of ma
terial minds, who deride all supernatural beliefs and
theories, hold to the opinion that after every great
war there is a wave of the occult in some form, and
say that right now the ouija board happens to be the g
most popular man-made medium of bringing together
terrestrial pinds and celestial beings and thoughts.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn89060379/1920-08-28/ed-1/seq-1</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045487/1917-04-02/ed-2/seq-16</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>tlence is supposed to be a woman
who lived in New England before the
revolution; her remarks are couched
in an old English form devoid of
modern words. She has "dictated"
poetry and stories, which Mrs. Cur
ran has read off as the pointer flew
from letter to letter on the ouija
board. The most amazing communica
tion, however, was that which re
quired the Currans to adopt a baby
and name it Patience Worth.
"Select a poor baby " was the de
mand, "and make all arrangements
for adoption before its birth."
So the Currans arranged with a
poverty-stricken prospective mother
for the adoption of her child, should
it be a girl.
The night of the baby's arrival a
session with the board was inter
rupted when Patience said:
"There be other things adoing."
Later it was found this interrup
tion came at the exact moment of
the baby's birth in a distant section
I of the city
2S--
Patience Worth
Mrs. J. H. Curran
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045487/1917-04-02/ed-2/seq-15</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>PATIENCE WORTH'S BABY!
Will This Child, Adopted at Direction of Ouija-
Board, Have the Power To Rip the Veil That
Enshrouds Future World?
7
St Louis, Mo., April 2. Will a
baby girl, a red-haired tot only a few
months old, be the child of destiny
who will sweep aside the veil which
separates the Here from the Here
after. Will Patience Worth, miracle baby,
whose adoption was directed by an
unseen hand, break down the bar
riers that prevent free communica
tion between the living and dead?
St. Louis today is asking these
questions as the remarkable infant
develops toward her first brithday at
the home of her foster-parents, Mr.
and Mrs. John H. Curran.
Interest in the child has spread far
beyond St Louis, for scientists study
ing psychic phenomena are asking:
Who is Patience Worth, the mys
terious personage who talks to the
Currans through their "weegee-board"?
-
How did she know the instant this
baby was born, and direct the Cur
rans as to her adoption?
Why are this baby's eyes, hair and
features exactly like those described
by the unseen "Patience" in a por
trait of herself?
And will this baby inherit from her
spiritual godmother the power to
bridge the gap between the world
and the after-life?
The baby Patience coos and crows
contentedly, little bothered by the
attention showered upon her, but al
ready enthusiasts of the Patience
cult are seeing in her eyes a far
away look which they interpret to
mean that the infant is receiving the
first dim communication from her
spiril-mother.
For several years the ouija-board
writings of Patience Worth have
been coming to Mrs. Curran. Pa-
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn90050268/1919-12-20/ed-1/seq-3</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>OUUA TELLS GIRL
SHE IS HEIR
TO FORTUNE
Mra. Jone. Learmt in Seance Wom
an Who Raised Her Was Not Her
Mother.
In^rnatlonal News Service.
Denver, Dec. 20.—The "Ouija
board mystery” that was revealed
here when Mrs. Adeline Jones, twen
ty-two, pretty Denver matron, dis
covered through the aid of the
“spirit slab” that she was not the
daughter of a woman who had cared
for her from childhood, has devel
oped into a search for persons and
I records extending from Indianapolis.
। Ind., to San Diego, Cal.
| Mrs. .lonel, living with Mrs. L.
j Snider, of this city, whom she had
, always believed to be her mother,
during a “seance” with the Ouija
| says a message came to her that
Mrs. Snider was not her mother, and
that her real mother was living in
Indiana.
Confronted with the request for
an explanation, Mrs. Snider is said
to have confessed that she was not
the mother of Mrs. Jones, but refus
ed to divulge any further informa
tion.
Mrs. Jones appealed to local po
lice for assistance in finding her
mother, telling them that the Ouija
board message had related a strange
tale of her mother living in Indiana;
that her father, who was supposed
to have been wealthy, had been mur
dered and that she was the rightful
heir to a substantial fortune.
Denver police interested them
selves in the case upon the admission :
by Mrs. Snider that she was not the
young woman's mother, and an in
veatigation has confirmed part of
the story told by the Ouija board.
The "Door of Hope." mentioned,
Mrs. Jones said, in the Ouija board
message, was formerly an orphan
asylum in Indianapolis, it was learn
ed by police of that city with whom
local officers comm inicated. It has
long since been dismantled and the
Florence Crittenden Home now occu
pies the site of the "Door of Hope"
in the Indiana capital.
Indianapolis police have been un.
able to locate the birth record of
Mrs. Jones, saying that the records
of twenty-two years ago were not
available, but through information
secured by Indianapolis detectives it
was disclosed that Mrs. Celia Smock.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn93061777/1920-07-15/ed-1/seq-2</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>OUIJA BOARD INVENTOR
MAKES A MILLION
With William Fuld cf Baltimore,
it has been GO 50, tit-for-tnt, an eye
for an eye, ar rather a dollar for a
splinter. He went to work and made
the ouija board and now the ouija
board has made $1,000,000 for him.
A cool million out of the ouija board
and that's a conservative estimate.
Mr. Fuld said it was conservative
and that he should know, he's a con
servative man and you'd think he's be
wearing a silk Palm Beach suit and a
half-pound diamond ring. Instead,
when he told a reporter that $1,000,
000 was a conservative estimate of
ouija board profits he had just come
from painting shutters in the back
yard and wore a pair of trousers
that the junk man wouldn't have paid
60 cents for without weeping.
"Believe in ouija board," Mr. Fuld
laughed heartily. "I should say not,
I'm no spiritualist, I'm a Presbyteri
an; been one over since I was so
high." There you are ouija folks,
Mr. Fuld makes the only original
ouija board patented in the
United Stales and trade marked all
over the world, but he wouldn't trust
it with so much as a question about
ths weather,
        </text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/2010218505/1915-12-10/ed-1/?sp=1</id>
    <results>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/2010218505/1915-12-10/ed-1/?sp=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>BROTHERHOODS CONSIDER
CALLING GENERAL STRIKE
/NEXT ?PRING
EIGHT HOUR
DAY DEMANDED I
Overtime Pay Also. Wanted-I
Leaders Declare There Will
Bs no Arbitration.
Chicago,' Dec. 9.-Presidents -o?
four unions, the brotherhoods of lo
comotive engineers, firemen, railway!
trainmen and railway conductors ar
rived i";?ro and held a secret confer
ence to consider the calling of a gen
eral -Htrlkc on all railroads In the
country next spring unless the lines
grant an eight hem- day and time and j
a halt for tfvertime.
The leaders declare that this time
there will hi; no arbitration, because
last spring arbitration gare only a
small part of tho wage l?crense de
manded and the mou are dissatisfied.
Timothy Eft ea, assistant to thc
president ol tho firemen, dntimated
that the conference might decide to
make. additional demands. Ho said
that "thy strike would involvo 350,000
men.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88077379/1915-12-25/ed-1/?sp=2</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>WILL DEMAND
EIGHT-HOUR DAY
Four Itailroad l!ro herlioods to Vote
Upon Demands.
Chicago., III. Presidents of the four
brotherhoods of railway trainmen start
ed to work today preparing the ballot
that is to be sent to the 100,000 employes
of the -LIS railroads in the United States
asking their approval of these demands:
An eight hour day, with the same
wages now paid for working ten hours.
Time and one-half for working over
time. These demands, completed here last
flight by officials of the Brotherhood
of Locomotive Firemen and Engine
men, Order of Railroad Conductors,
Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers,
and Brotherhood of Railway Train
men, will be mailed to every member
of the four organizations on January
1, it was announced. They will be
given sixty days in which to vote and
return their ballots. After all ballots
have been relumed, officials of the four
organizations will meet in Chicago,
probably in April, to agree on a date
for presenting the result of the vote to
the railroads.
It. It. WlltK .MK.V KAIHIO WAGHS.
Cincinnati, O. Big Four Railroad
telegraphers have raised wages i per
cent as a result of compromises agreed
to between their representatives and
the company.
STATU UNIONISTS TO MHKT.
Louisville, Ky. Officers of the State
Federation of Labor have issued a call
for the annual convention to be held
in this city, beginning Monday, January
ID.
STItlKi: Oh1 KlSIIIOItS lONDS.
lioston, Mass. The four weeks'
strike of fishermen against the hay
State Fishing Company has ended with
an agreement satisfactory to these
workers. Hours of labor arc to be re
duced. IKON MOIiDDKK NTItlKK.
Pittsburg, Pa. In an effort to es
tablish the eight-hour day in this vicin
ity, about 1,500 iron molders are on
strike.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85058396/1916-09-02/ed-1/?sp=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>RAILROAD MANAGERS LIFT ALL I
EMBARGOES, SEEING PEACE AHEAD I
Brotherhoods Decide Not to Cancel Walk-out Order Until
President Wilson Actually Signs Proposal Designed to
Prevent Recurrence of Present Situation; Tension jl
Due to Fear of General Tie-up Relaxes as
Problem Finds Its Own Solution. 'H
Washington, Sept. 2. The senate late today rejected the
Underwood amendment to the Adamson bill which would give 'H
the Interstate Commerce Commission authority to fix rail- 'H
road wages and hours of service. The vote was 14 to 57.
The senate also rejected Senator Newlands' amendment to
make interference with the operation of trains a misdemeanor
punishable by fine and imprisonment. Senator Thomas with
drew a similar amendment. The vote on the Newlands
amendment was 14 to 52.
Washington, Sept. 2.- The Adamson eight-hour bill, ac
cepted by labor union officials as providing a satisfactory set
tlement of the demands on which they base their order calling
a nation-wide railroad strike for Monday, was passed without
amendment by the senate tonight and now awaits only Presi
dent Wilson's signature to make it a law. Revocation of the IH
strike order is expected within a few hours. 11
The Brotherhood men have called off the strike.
Washington. Sept 2. At a meeting
of the 13 brotherhood officials in
Washington today it was formally de
cided that cancellation of the strike
order should not be sent out until
President Wilson actually has signed
the etght-hour bill. Another meeting
of the officials will be field tonight
after the senate has acted on the
house bill.
At this time there is a possibility
that the decision might be changed.
Washington, Sept 2. The enact
ment into law of enough of President
Wilson's program to prevent the rail
way strike seemed reassured when
congress reasembled this morning ot
10 o'clock with a program that calls
for a vote not later than 6 o'clock
this evening. It was the belief of ad
ministration leaders that the Adamson
bill as it passed the house late yester
day, approved by President Wilson
and formally accepted by the labor
leaders as meeting their demands,
would eventually be accepted by the
senate, thus obviating a conference to
reconcile differences was possible.
As soon as the perfected bill finally
is passed a special messenger will
carry it to tho summer White House
at Shadow Lawn so the president may
sign it at once and end the menace of
a general paralysis of the country's
transportation lines at 7 o'clock Mon
day morning.
(Continued on page 13.)
oo
RAILROADS CALL
OFF EMBARGOES
Abandon Preparations for War
as Congress Work to Se
cure Peace.
Managers Hold No Meetings,
Believing Adamson Bill
Will Pass Senate.
Chicago, Sept 2. Railroads of the
country abandoned preparations for
war today and rewarded to those for
peace. From all over the country
railroad heads railroad heads an
nounced that embargoes placed on
shipments as a war measure, were re
voked. In Chicago the usual meeting of rail
road presidents was not held, nor did
the executive committee of the General
Manager's association issue the cus
tomary statement It was assumed
that the Adamson bill would pass the
senate tonight that the strike order
would bo recalled, and that trains
would run as usual Mondny morning,
the date set for the walkout
Feeling assured that the strike or
der will bo cancelled, tho following
railroads today revoked their embar
goes: Chicago, Milwaukee and St Paul;
Chicago and Alton; Chicago, Rock Is
land and Pacific; Chicago and North
western; Monon; Chicago and Eastern
Illinois; Chicago Great Western, and
the Illnols Central. The Chicago,
Burlington and Quincy revoked last
night Western railroad heads said
that they xinderstood eastern roads
would tako similar action In the
course of the day.
Omaha, Neb., Sept. 2. At President
Calvin's office today It was announced
that the strike embargo on freight
had been raised by the Union Pacific
and tho Oregon Short Line.
San Francisco, Calif., Sept. 3. The
Southern Paclfio railroad revoked its
strike Embargo today on llvestook
and perishable freight throughout its vk
thousands of miles of lines.
Denver, Colo., Sept. 2. The Colora- jH
do and Southern railroad today re- 'IH
voked its embargo on all classes of ll
freight.
The Denver Rio Grande railroad
today removed. all restrictions on
freight shipments over its lines, it
was announced at headquarters here. WM
St. Paul, Minn., Sept 2. The Chi- i
cago, St Paul, Minneapolis, and Oma
ho railway today revoked Its embargo
on freight. The northern Pacific and
Great Northern roads were considering
modification or revocation of their em
bargo orders. 11
KH
Topeka, Kansas. Sept. 2. The At
chlson, Topeka and Santa Fe railroad VH
revoked Its freight embargo, accord
Ing to an announcement made hero Vl
today by J. R. Koonts, general freight
agent
Memphis, Tenn., Sept. 2. An
nouncement was made at the Yazoo 11
and Mississippi Valley freight offices
here today that all embargoes placed
on freight in connection with the JM
threatened railroad strike have been H
removed.
Fort Worth, Texas, Sept 2. All re
strlctions were removed from shipping IH
this morning by the Fort Worth and
Denver railroad.
Kansas City, Mo., Sept 2. Official
orders will go out from the general
offices of the Kansas Southern Rail Ijl
way here today lifting the freight em-
bargo tomorrow. 11
San Francisco Calif., Sept 2. The
Western Pacific railroad lifted today
its strike order embargo on all perish- WM
ables and livestock. IH
Dallas, Teas, Sept 2. Embargoes JH
on all classes of freight were raised IH
bv the following Texas railroads:
'Missouri, Oklahoma and Gulf; St.
Louis, San Francisco and Texas (Fris
co); Houston and Texas Central and
the Gulf, Colorado and Santa Fe, ac-
cording to an announcement from tho iH
several offices.
Los Angeles, Calif., Sept. 2. The
Los Angeles and Salt Lako railroad 'JH
lifted today its embargo on all per- 'w H
ishable and livestock freight 3
nn 41 11
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030193/1916-09-02/ed-1/?sp=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>STRIKE MAY BE
EVEN BEFORE THE PRESIDEN
GN
RAILROAD
Plans to Rush Bill to Wilson at the
Summer White House To-Night
Are Changed, and It Will Not Be
come a Law Until To-Mor row
Senate Debate Is Spirited.
CONGRESS BEING HELD UP,
DECLARE REPUBLICANS
WASHINGTON, Sept. 2. Despite the Republican opposition to the
Uight-I lour Bill in the Senate, Administration leaders, this afternoon gave
positive assurauce that there would I'e no r.iilroad strike Monday. They
declared the Senate certainly would pass th: Adamson bill. Nothing can
block It, they said, and so telegraphed President Wilson at Shadow Lawn
before the debate in the Senate began. Final voting on the bill will begin
at 6 o'clock.
Consideration nf tho time necessary to enroll and engross the bill
made It necessary to change plans for rushing It to the President at
Shadow l.awn to-night. It would bo Impossible to got the bill to him before
he leaves nn the return trip to Washington. Consequently It la now plannad
to liavo him a Tlx his signature during the short stop he makes In Wash
Ington to-morrow, before leaving for llodgenvllle, Ky.
11 Decision to cancel the strike' order
LIEUT. ROBERT FAY,
F
Bomb Plotter Is Held Prisoner
at Corinth, Miss. He Re
fuses to Make Statement.
COlllNni. Miss., Bopt. 1. Unit.
Hubert Pay, who escaped from tho
Federal penitentiary at Atlantic, Cla
a few days ago, was arrested here to
day. Tho Lieutenant was convicted nt
New York ss the leader In a botnb
plot to blow up ships carrying war
fupplloa and munitions to the allies.
When Identified here to-day he ro
fused to make any statement.
WHITMAN AND SEABURY
TO FIGHT IN PRIMARIES
Legal Action to Void Governor's
Independence League Petition
Is Discontinued.
KINOHTON, N. Y Sept. 2. rro-
ceedlugs to have tho petition desig
nating Oov. Whitman for the Inde
pendence l.engun nomination for Gov
ernor declared null and voM because
of alleged forged signatures lu the
petition woro withdrawn before Bu
promo Court Justice Ilasbrouck to
day. Itoth Oov, Whitman nnd former
Judge Buiimel Bcabury have agreed
to contend for that nomination In tho
Independence League primary elec
tion. Mailman Nhonle I'p a Car anil Kills
llliii.rlf.
INDIANAPOLIS, llid., Kept. 2. Ono
Is dftiil and two injured as the result
of Tliomiu Dorsey becoming erased on
a eruwdril ear here lu-day and ftrlng a
number of shots down the aisle of the
car at his wife. Dorsey committed sui
cide when cornered in the car bv a
policeman, lUa wife Is Injured serious
ly. Another wesnan was shot fat he
WHO BROKE OUT 0
AIL
I CAPTURED
staea, u-w.J
CALLED OEF
T
E
only when the eight-hour bill becomes
a law was reached In a session of the'
thirteen remaining district brother
hood chairmen this afternoon. A. H.
Uarrotson, as chairman of the meet
ing, ruled that It Is n law only when
Prvsldont Wilson hns signed It.
MAY CANCEL 8TRIKC ORDER.
TO-NIQHT.
Another meeting will be held to
nlxht, however, after tha bill passes,
and it may be decided then to send
the cancellation orders to-night.
Although Senate leaders practically
agreed to pass tho measure adopted
by the House there was spirited de
bate. Tho first amendment proposed to
day came from Benator Shafrotb,
Democrat, ll'i proposed to fix Sen
ator Underwood's uincndment em
powering the Interstate Commerce
Commission to inako wage schedules
so that no employee would be com
pelled to work for tho rate prescribed.
Senator Bhafrnth opened the debate
by moving to chuuge Henator Under
wood's amendment so that It would be
specifically stated no employee af
fected by the b'il would be compelled
by Its terms to work, that stopping
of work would not constitute "delay
ing or obstructing operation of
trains," for which the amendment
provides a fine of 3,000 or one year's
Imprisonment.
"Suppose," said Senator Hardlwlck,
"the ralldoad presidents came to ua
and said; 'Legislate ua Increased
freight or passenger rates or we will
atop operating, all trains In this coun.
try.' What would we do? We would
not be permitted to bo coerced."
CHIEF INTEREST 18 TO AVERT
STRIKE.
Why don't you Hepubllcr-e atop
criticising and offer some'.,V, to
avert this Btrlker querlodSLauV.
Wisconsin. "1 think we all agreo the
main question, our chief interest, la
to avert this Impending calamity. Be
we shall do It In tha only possible
way by legislation."
Honator Sherman, Illinois, bitterly
denounced "rushing the bill Into leg
islation In a few hours when thore
should bo days of deliberation." "We
am doing this under threat."
To prove ills point, he read several
telegrams from large labor unleaa at
the Middle Weet steading with. MeB
MEAD
Jfcfcl
V
at A
A ,-tJ" Sl 'ti-tli
MiauaU.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86088527/1916-09-03/ed-1/?sp=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Eight Hour Day Law
Enacted By The Senate
Averts Industrial War
PRESIDENT HURRYING BACK TO WASHINGTON
FROM HIS SUMMER HOME IN NEW JERSEY TO SIGN
ADAMSON BILL, WHICH WILL BECOME LAW OF
THE LAND BEFORE fJREAKFAST TIME SUNDAY
MORNING.
PAHTV LINES TIGHTLY
Willi Ona Exceplion Republicnn Scimlors Bitterly- Fought
Mcaanre thnl Snve lite Nation front Great CUmity
Rnilrond Prcaidcnta Decide Nol lo Tsko ny Precipitata
Court Actiun to Test Conililntionnlity of the Law.
LONG IJRANCI I, Now Jersey. Sept. 2.U wns nn
nounced tonight llmt Proaiilont WilKon would bibii the cinltt
hour hill itt 7 30 o'clock tomortow inorniitR.
Whon tolil tonight Hint the eijiht hotir hill M"ni rendy for
his siannturo Prowitlant Wiloon mild: "It is the climtxx of
vory Imppy day."
WASHINGTON, Sept. 2.
of rnilrond umployns which htm
try for n nionlli. wna lifted
onutc Imd nnwed the Admmon
mum. the liancltt ol tour Kicat rnilroiul brotherhoous tele-
Sntphod nix huudiochodd code munrnyea to their Kcnursl
mirmen in nil pnrtu of the country, auicellin? the strik;o onlcr
thnl would htive become effective nt eoven o'clock Monday
iiiorniiiK
The leuitlntivo cxocdlent to avert tltti stiikn was mmied
eo,mle ,JV vo,c tofty
tt Airict v nnriv void, nmid
USU,U0" U,'U COnK! 5S IVTlS.DqiUH coerccu II
of loyinlatioii tt did not deidro and that it knew would return
to plnuup it in the future. Tito inenNtirc wan hittned by thn
nroaidmg officer of both houaes within ten ininutea after it
Imd iiMcd the Nannte and sent to the White I Joiuc, where
Prewitlut Wilson will inn it early tomorrow.
Brotherhood officials, who witnenaed the final nnuiniieof
the bill, had announced early
J u, I,: -tnnnltit I in ulrikft nrnvidnn llml nfter IllnunrV
'j-..T-y
first, next, oight hours will bo
trainmen ctiKiiKcd in interstate
iltws limn one hundred miles lonR. and that they receive prorata
py for work in cxcciis of eiuht
I I r ...f
lion not to be changed for n period of from six to nine moiitlv
p0ndmK an invest uatton by a
P.
inoiuted by the president.
j All rfforts to amaud the bill in the senate were futile,
I Only two domocrats, I lardwlck of Georgia and Clnrkeof Ar4
kansas, voted agninNt the bill, and one republican, LnFollelle
i of Wisconsin, voted for it,
Railroads assert that the bill will cost them sixty million
dollurs annually in increased wawes to trainmen. The brother-
hoods claim that the annual increase will be only twenty mil
lions, in conyross and amonir railway officials there exist
fJf,.,ia n in illr, mnstittitinnntilv nf lliit. law. but what uteris to
,r
losi hub. ii any, wui,oe niKen,
Ihorc is no doubt but that

inn lomorrow as ii emurnr.e
i llf I 'VI A
legislative profnm he took before congress last Uuiroay,
NO HASTY COURT ACTION.
CHICAGO. Sept. 2. Accepting the passage of the
A 1 t Ml I... .1 i t.t
uamsun um oy uie ceiiiun toiiinni an compicic itnaurnirt.c iihi
llm ili.tirrrir' ttf n lr!l-rt luirl njiikr'fl lii'wln nf uifititrM mllroatla
nnuoutjcd this evening that they would take no preciniUitisl.
ourt action against law, but watt until thct measure ltfs Bmw
'thoroughly investigated. At the same time thy decWred that
preparations for the strike had cost the railroads well mto tlto
,,n i
j millions. I lie prceiUCIllH B.IIU me ijkiuuuu inirc inwm jrrircii
t,c foaJH wcrc ready for the test and that n large ercent of
...ll I n.iLl.J l.J- j
limn iiicii ntuvmi iiul linvu uiiw
Hug,
n -t I
iviany raiiroaus arjnounccu
jed off because ho wanted the
I test. He W the eight hour
joy tn railroads.
4.
DRAWN ON LEGISLATION
The threat of n Benaral strike
been hnnuittK over the coun
toniuht. Three hours nfter tlt
oiht hour kill without amend.
throb lo Iwcnly-ciRht. ahnot
aUrrinn Kcat.tttt. Some nciVBtom
into the cmicTnwnT
tonight hat cancellation of the
J- .-,,T
regarded as n day's work for
commerce, cxcmptinu ronds
houia, the rale of compensa-
..I -f t ..I ...I
commiss on of three to lie ap-
i' i I
nns noi yci nccn inuicaiqu.
President Wilson will nign U

vimiany iiii um prupunuiH iu ins
um. uiuuiviiiuvu una'.
l .1.- i.!.i!. .t? ltJM
nicy were srium on um.
quion to oo,U. a fxM
kw would aurely be contest</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1917-01-07/ed-1/?sp=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>STRIKECALLON
AGAIN IMPENDS
Brotherhood Leaders Feel They
Were "Buncoed" by Last
Congress.
CHIEFS TO MEET THURSDAY
Men Oppose New Adamson Bill
Providing Straight Eight
hs Hour Day.
The threat of a general railroad
strike, paralyzing the nation trans
portation and business, was renewed
today.
Following a. conference between
"Warren 8. Stone, grand chief of the
Brotherhood of Xocomotlve Engi
neers, and H. E. .Lewis, legislative
agent of that brotherhood, the word
went out that "a strike call is more
than a possibility."
The feeling of railroad leaders that
they were "buncoed" in the legisla
tion adopted by the last Congress to
avert a rail strike, and the bitter
opposition the rail leaders feel to the
Adamson hill, introduced yesterday,
to "put teeth" in the Adamson law.
now under Are. have combined to
create a new strike crisis.
Labor Chiefs Meet Thursday.
President Stone, of the engineers,
at the Willard today, refused to make
an authoritative statement, as he
has not yet conferred with his asso
ciate railroad leaders.
A conference of chiefs of the tour
brotherhoods will be held at Chicago
Thursday. There were reports today
that at this conference a strike call
may He-issued, under the blanket au
thority given their leaders by the
men. Mr. Stone would not discuss
this.
"The railroad brotherhoods will not
be represented by counsel when argu
ments in the Adamson law are heard
by the United States Supreme Court
tomorrow," President Stone said to
day. Mr. Stone added that be would
be present to hear the arguments.
President Stone would not discuss
the new Adamson bill, which is de
signed to supplement the present
Adamson Jaw, but it Is knows he is
unalterably opposed to 1U provisions.
Iindifs 0pee Xrw Mil
Other labor leaders attacked the
new Adamson bill aa distinctly in
imical to the interest of theSaenThe
provisions 'of the sew bill which the
railroad men will oppose are:
That preventing any railroad em
ploye from 'working more than eight
hour without the consent of the In
terstate Commerce Commission.
That providing compulsory arbitra
tion and prohibiting strikes while
rail disputes are under investigation.
That empowering fhe President to-i
commandeer and operate the lines of
railroads while strikes are pending,
which it is feared would compel the
men to remain in operation of trains
while disputes were under arbitra
tion. Straight Eight-Hour Law.
'The "railroads have said the pres
ent Adamson law la a wage law and
not -an eight-hour law," Congress
man Adamson said today in explana
tion of his new measure. "The new
hill Is a straight out-and-out eight
hour law."
Railroad brotherhood leaders have
resisted eight-hour legislation In the
past. What they have sought is the
(Continued on Page Fourteen.)
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030193/1917-01-08/ed-1/?sp=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Insists 8 -Hour Law Is 'Constitutional and Workable!
1
To-Day'i Weatrftr FAIK AND COLDER.
"Clrctilatlqn Books Open to All."
I "Oirculntlon Books Open toAll."
PRICE ONE CENT.
CoprMlM, 1117. Iir The l'rM I'uMUhlng
Co. Tlie New Vnr tTurlil.
NEW YORK, MONDAY, JANUARY 8, 1917. 14 PAGES
PRICE ONE CENT, 'i
FMAli
Jjl CDTOA j
TO
Jff 1 CDTOV
iV.
1
LAWSON, GRILLED, IN ANGER CONFESSES
HE HAS NOT ANY PEACE 'LEAK EVIDENCE
CONGRESS HAS POWER 10 EIK
RAILROAD WAGES, U. S. HOLDS
IN EIGHT-HOUR TEST SUIT
Arguments on the Adamson
Act Are Begun Before the
Supreme Court.
RIGHT TO AVERT STRIKE.
Federal Brief Asserts Railways
First Admitted the Law
Was Obeyable.
WASHI-VOTON. Jan. 8. Annul
ment of Unltrd State Clicult Judge
Hook's decision holding tho Adam
son Eight-Hour Law unconstitutional
and dismissal ot tlic railroad's suit
w asked In tho brief of the Depart
ment of Justice filed In tho Supreme
Court to-day.
"As an hours of service" net and
Ulo wage law. the Federal brief
.'Contended, "the law Is constitutional,
within the power of Congress to
enact and workable."
InfeYcntlully, the brief argued that
compulsory arbitration legislation, I
such us Is under consideration, uliio
Is constitutional In behalf of public
interests to prevent tle-upi of trans-,
portatton facilities.
Practicability of obeying the law,
the brief asserted, has been admitted
galn and ugnln by railroad official,
particularly In hearings before Con
gressional committees hist August
and In confeicnces with PreMdent i
Wilson.
"All assumed thut the mere change
from tho established and well-under-atood
ten-hour standard day to thr
proposed elght-hour standurd was all
that wftK necessary or Intondeil," the
brief stated, citing that 85 pur cent, of
the employees affected are now em
ployed on a ten-hour basis.
Admitting that a rigid eight-hour
day for train operation not com
pletely practicable, the Federal nttor
neys said tho Adamson law should be
enforced at least so far ns Is possible.
"Two co-ordluute branches of thn
Oovernmcnt have evidenced the opin
ion that the law Is constitutional,"
the brief continued. "Certnlnly this
court will not strike down the law
upon mere prophecies of Its effect."
Alleged Infringement of tho liberty
of contract, It was contended, docs not
affect tho act's validity, nor "tho as
sertion that Congress enacted this
lav from Improper motives and upon
InMifDclont information."
Arguing for the supreme -power of
Congress over Interstate commerce,
tho brief Hald:
"In tho Adamson law the Idea of
the Board of Arbitration 'has been
adopted by direct action, rather than
through a board. Wane regulation
has a vital connection with Interstate
commerce. Congress's power Is ample
enough to authorize direct control
over the wage relation of persons en
gaged In interstate- comment. There
certainly falls within that power the
right to take all steps necessary to
put down n strlko or prevent an Im
pending one." I
A Vil.. n'aa fill..! I.,' l.ritiL-

H"e.n ?.C,a,'
a iKt La uui i.i n.tu.nui in kid
Hagerman contended tho railroads
had previously admitted but now deny 1
the law Is capable of operation. Judge
Hook, uo natd, sustained its prac
ticability by ordoring tho railroads
to keep spodal account of wages due
employees under tho law to Insure
their prompt payment If It Is sui-
talned by the Huprome Court,
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85032923/1917-01-10/ed-1/?sp=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>DEPARTMENT JUSTICE
ASKS FOR ANNULMENT
OF DECISION BY CIR
CUIT JUDGE HO.OK.
WASHINGTON, Jan. S. The cli
max in the test over the constitution
alitv of the Adamson law was reached
today in the Supreme court.
Arguments were begun In the Mis
souri, Oklahoma and Gulf railroad's
test case, in which the department of
justice is appealing from Federal
Judge Hook's decision at Kansas City,
that the law passed last September
when a nation-wide railroad strike
seemed imminent, is "unconstitution
al, null and void."
Voluminous briefs were filed by the
Federal and railroad counsel before
the beginning of the arguments which
proceeded after announcement by the
court of numerous opinions and or
ders on reconvening after Its holiday
recess. Numerous precedents, includ
ing Supreme court decisions, were
cited in the department of justice
brief in support of the law's validity.
1 he railroad s brief contended that
the law is unworkable, experimental.
incapable of application, interferes
with liberty of contract, docs not fall
within congress's authority to regu
late interstate commerce and takes
railroad property without "due pro
cess" of law.
The arguments were begun by coun
sel for the dcplrtmcnt of justice.
which has sole charge of the defense,
the railroad brotherhoods not appear
ing officially.
Annullmcnt of Circuit Judge Hook's
decision holding the Adamson law
unconstitutional and dismissal of the
railroad's suit was asked in the brief
of the department of justice.
As the hours of service act and
also as a wage law, the Federal brief
contended the law is constitutional,
within the power of congress to en
act, and workable. Infcrentially, the
brief argued that compulsory arbitra
tion legislation, such as under con
sideration ,also is constitutional in be
half of public interests to prevent
tie-ups of transportation facilities.
Practicability of obeying the law,
the brief asserted, has been admitted
again and again by railroad officials,
particularly in hearings before con
gressional committees last August,
and in conferences with President
Wilson.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id></id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>ixaiiway Jtieaas urantHj
Men's Demands in
Face of Crisis
,v
U. S. COURT DECIDES fl
ACT CONSTITUTIONAL?!
Majority Opinion, However,-
Denies Labor's Right to
SfvilfP in Warro Pnw
""fe-""' 81
SUCCESS OF
MEDIATORS-!
Magnates Praised for Patriotism
as Trainmen Clamor for
Private Rights
The threatened nation-wide strike of
100,000 railway workmen has been
averted through the patriotic act of the
railway officials in granting to the
trainmen virtually all they demanded.
President Wilson's arbitration board?".
was empowered by the roads 'to effect jis
any settlement in view ot trie ucrman raj
Will CHS1S.
The board authorized the application
of the terms of the Adamson law, giv
ing an eight-hour day with ten hours
pay.
Following this agreement and after
the strike had been averted, the Unitedi
States Supremo Court decided the
Adamson law was constitutional.
The basis of the court decision was
that Congress has the right, in the'
face of a national crisis, to legislates
even to the extent of wage regulation,
when narties to a controversy fail or
lefuse to act. This does not destroy, k
hut. Kimprsedes nrivntfl richts in win' f
fixing. j;$
The Supreme Court rules, however, jm
mat no group oi railway woricers nasry
the right to strike in concert, whea3l
wages arc in controversy.' This is re-4jl
garaea a most important icaturc oi. ur.
decision. s STI
.sa
ADAMSONAcrVALtDTi.
SUPREME COURT RULES
WASHINGTON. March 19.
son eight-hour law Is valid.
-The Adam-w
r j
This Is ther
ruling of the United States Supreme Court W
today,
divided
The decision was arrived at by a M
court, the Chief Justice and five .rM
.j
of his associates holding the law const!- JS
tutlonal.
Chief Justice White read the decision
ii'ltlnti hiqIaq 'nltl 4Ha inu" nno.nd iinrip
ftjiffjjj
night hours of last summer's Congress scs- ,aM
t...i..- t.. i i..i.i i.t....., ...a tfltH
Biuu. uu?iu:u iy3 in uciiuil wi llllliscii. tiuu jbrjft
Justices Pitney and v andewatcr, read the
dissenting opinion as soon as the Chief Jus-
tlce had concluded.
The right of a group of railroad worker
to utr'Ur In ronrert an n result of nmf
differences were denied. In the course. of the ,itKjJ
majority opinion, by Chief Justice Whit. J
This principle may readily prove the mostj
Important of the decision, as the dangerji
or a naiion-wuie siiikc was averted eariyfyCJI
today before the court passed an opiniqit."jjjsrr
Knowledge that the supreme i-ourt noma .wjr
this view Is apt to have a pronounced ef- M
feet on future attempts Dy rauroaa worKers3
to better their conditions. ,J
necessarily surrendered when the men are
engaged In the public serTlce. They are.
COmparaOie lO puiuivia ill llio mimo, nuw vfi
the presence of enemies
oi incir country .o.
may not desert."
llesldes declaring the Adamson
law cea
stltutlonat the highest tribunal held Cos.i,,
gress had a right to legislate ihism.
Tho Supreme Court's decision Is a formal i
reversal of tho opinion of Judge William C,'l
Hook. Kansas City, who held the law un-sy
nn,i Mntlnnnl. t
Chief Justice White, in his opinion, coni.
eluded
We say that the contention that the
act wns void and could rot be made
operative because of '.he nnworkibUlty
of Its provisions Is nrtllio'tc merP., sine
we see no rrnson to dontit that If the
s'tandard fixed by the act were mad
applicable and a candid effort followed
to carry It out, the result wouia oe
without difficulty accomplished. It la
trus that It might folov that in some
cases that because of particular terms
oi employment or rAjc,Juui.. ouiiuu..-
Inn-a enn-ia tA.'.T.V mlcfht lift nPRMJV. A? J
m 1 .-Ak4iMMl MIS M M e
SJ0 DU'lIU bllHIIRv "--T m m ,J i jup.
imt these exceptions onora no srounu
for lioldinE' the act votu. Because vm ny
nimiitBlniia Ofj tint QliaritMIr tk 111 tirill
UCCOl ucilltf WHioy uuii
ueing oi me uhiiiuii iiiv v.w,i'wo
had th? power to adopt the act In. quee- -7.
tlon. whether It be viewed as; a direct Si i
fixing of wages to meet the absence W it
a btandard on that sujecr reauittaf
from the dispute between yt partletef
as the exertion ot ino power or v
gress .which It undoubtedly fMue
la nroTlde by appropriate lech
for comDulsory BrbltralUiv-. I
widely IncTltablr resulted fr,HHI
tnorlty to preieci iswr.ww
in iin' with a, sltuaon
which, was beter. It we conclttajfl
the 'court below erred Jn hoMak
statute was not witmn tua,l
Congresa to ena
enforcement.
nuet be and I
cause .remand
UMlaa Ae bill,
White did m
statemeiit dnf
print, opinion.
"Air.tli
unedi
ooma't ,twft i
i VrJrir,'
'K
m
ca
m
v
tsJfcr
3
Kft
ras
TO
i

"g
a 42
rwifiBFiir nfl-tft tO
T
MM tiUMmm lfr V
?X'i.
lA.iaultlU..-j. fc...
v'lilM'ilaffiliaifiiiTl i
;3M
jw
4 SWkwmiHHM!ULaamaWLmaWLmaaaaaWLm9
Fit screen
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1917-03-19/ed-1/?sp=1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>ADAMSONLAW
IS HELD VALID
United States Supreme Court
Rules Congress Has Flight
to Fix Wages.
"Validity of-th Adamson elght-hoor
law was upheld today by the United
Stites Supreme Court In a decision
which affirmed the right of Congress
to Hx wages.
The official line-up of the justices,
as given by Clerk Maher, of the Su
preme Court, was that McRe'ynolds
dissented, with Day, Pitney and Van
Deventer. McReynolds was said to
have conceded that Congress had the
wage-flxing power only in view of the
court's decision, and his name did not
appear on the court record as dissent
ing. Maher's version, which is official,
however, made the division five to
four with Chief Justice White and
Justices McKenna. Holmes, Brandels
and Clark constituting the majority
in favor of the law.
Justice McKenna read a separate opin
ion giving views slightly divergent 'from
those of the Chief Justice.
Justice McReynolds. while he concur
red, was not flatly In favor. He was
classed as doubtful, but In a short
statement he conceded Congress the
arage fixing power and, in effect, con
curred. Head Dissenting Opinions.
1
Pitney and Day rend dissenting opin
ion.. Van-Deventerconcurred with lit
Bey ami. In part, with Day.
Chief Justice White read the de
cision which makes constitutional the
law passed under spectacular circum
stances In the closing night hours of
last summer's Congress session.
The Supreme Cturt's decision today
Is a ?ormaf reversal of the opinion of
Judge William C. Hook, of Kansas
City, who held the law unconstitu
tional. Justice White said "there was an
authority begotten of the public In
terest" in Congress action.
He derlared.lt could not be main
tained as the railroads had that the
law had not been ronsldered.,ln view,
first, of the time the controversy was
before the public; second, of the fact
that the President had acted, and,
third. In view of the discussion of the
uestlon before Congress acted.
Provisions of Law.
The Adamson eight-hour law pro
vides that, beginning January 1
(last) eight hours shall. In contracts
for labor and service, be deemed a
day's work, and the measure and
standard of a da.i work for the
purposes of leckonlng compensation
for services of all employes who now
or hereafter may be employed by any
common carrier by railroad, except
railroads Independently owned and
operated and not excelling 100 miles
In length, electric street railroads,
and electric lnleriirban railroads.
1'nder Section 2. the President Is
ordered to appoint a commission of
three, to investigate and report "on
effects of operation of the law, espe
dally as regards the effect of the
necessary pay Increases. This com
mission Is to report Its findings to
the President and Congress within
from six to ten months from date of
organization.
Section 3, which haa been called
the wage legislating clause, is that,
pending the commission's report,
compensation shall not be reduced
below the present standard, and for
all time In excess of eight hours em
ployes affected shall be paid at a rate
not less than the pro rata rate fpr
such standard eight-hour work day.
Section 4 provides S100 to 11.000
fine or a year's Imprisonment, or
boUvfoc violation.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045487/1916-02-22/ed-1/seq-27</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>LABOR UNIONS START FIGHT FOR UNIVERSAL
EIGHT-HOUR DAY!
Stirring scene from the second act of "The Weavers," showing the re
bellious employes of the labor tyrant who exploits the handloom weavers,
aroused by the singing of a fabor hymn. "The Weavers" tells the story of
the downtrodden Sjlesian working people in 1840. The drama caused a
revulsion of feeling in Germany, and was one of the bits of propaganda
that brought about a vast betterment of working conditions.
New York, Feb. 22. An eight-hour
day for every workingman!
That is the object of a great cam
paign just launched the first in
America by the Labor Center asso
ciation in New York.
Millions of striking poster stamps
will carry the message to all corners
of the country. Every union man
and. union sympathizer is asked to
use these stamps on all his corre
spondence to spread it broadside
under the eyes of his fellow-workers,
employers and the general public.
With 400,000 railway employes
threatening a strike unless they get
the eight-hour day, and the coal
miners doing the same, it is evident
this campaign is to have the greatest
publicity in the history of organized
labor!
Women garment workers through
out the country are expected to fol
low the 60,000 now on strike in New
York for snorter working hours.
And straphangers please note It
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045487/1916-09-12/ed-1/seq-27</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>NO EIGHT-HOUR DAY FOR THIS GIRL-WORKS
LONG HOURS FOR MOVIE FAME
- ?
li I 'HIP Mi ' I I HI ' Ml i r ' 1,m,l
8 XIxtflHBP SSjg
VrrgsL Photo LA."
Miss Roberta Wilson, vivaciousis still nothmg unusual for her to -pit
, "fceauty of ttfe movies, who scorns
the idea of an eight-hour day. She
ias reached the heights in her work
only through the most serious sort or
in 16 hourfc out of the 24 in her
studies of the photoplay. She and
her company have just completed a
trip along the 750-mile coast lirfe -of
California in the making of a new
trying and declares that it was and production.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045487/1915-03-19/ed-1/seq-1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>BATTLE FOR EIGHT-HOUR DAY IS ON
BEFORE ILLINOIS LEGISLATURE
Dudley Taylor of Restaurant Bosses Leads5Big Business
Lobby Against Medill IcCormick's MLWomen.
Workers Lead Labor's FigKt
"
r Dudley Taylor was not in conrt
representing the restaurant bosses
yesterday in their fight on the -waitresses
union. Instead of represent
ing them in this' city he "was in
Springfield lobbying in opposition to
the women's eight-hour day bm
which is now being considered by the
house industrial relations committee.
At the close of her speech boosting
the bill Taylor asked Agnes Nestor,
pres. Women's Trade Union league,
if "you wouldn't be ready to accept
nine hours as a compromise."
Miss Nestor replied she had no au
thority to accept a. compromise.
'"Who do you represent?"' Rep.
Medil McCormick asked Taylor.
"iNone of yf tor business," replied
Taylor.
After a. warn argument the chair
man ruled that the lofefeyfets need' got
reveafce names of all their princi
pals until "Hr came time for their set
addressee.
Oscar -F. "Nelson, state factory in
spector told of the weaknesses of
the present tenhour law' and sug
gested changes in form for the new
law if enacted.
"The. -same argument against this
bill was used against the eight-hour
law for miners," said pres. John
Walker of the EL Federation of
Labor. "Now, every operator in the
state will admit the conditions are
better than they were before. I per
sonally favor an eight-hour day for
everybody, and that Is the end to
ward which we are striving."
EUaaheih Maloney of the Chicago
Waitresses' Union told how their ten
hour day was stretched over into a
12 and sometimes 13-hosr period,
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn78000395/1907-04-06/ed-1/seq-1</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>NORFOLK PRINTERS
SETTLE GRIEVANCE
NORFOLK, Va., March 28.—An
agreement was reached today between
the proprietors and journeymen print­
ers of Norfolk and Portsmouth where­
by the printers will receive a substan­
tial Increase in pay beginning March
27. The agreement calls for the eight- .,
hour day and morning newspaper
printers will receive an increase from
$19 to $21 per week afternoon news­
paper printers from $17 to $19 per
week. Book and job printers receive
an increase from 32 Mi cents to 35 cents
per hours.
GRANT EIGHT-HOUR DAY. *J
The United Brethren Publishing^
house, of Dayton, which refused its
employes the eight-hour day last year,
is now endeavoring to sidestep the ad­
verse criticism which has been shower­
ed upon them by announcing that they
will grant their employes the eight
hour day beginning January 1, 1909
What do you think of that? The
managers of this truly Christian in­
stitution, which by the way. does gen
eral commercial printing for profit,
Will grant the eight-hour day in 1909,
They are certainly liberal, and no
doubt the strike-breakers at present
In their employ were jubilant when
they learned that they would get the
eight-hour day in "1909." "l
It Is apparent on the face of it fiat
the management is trying to evade the
stigma which has been placed on the
publishing house by its treatment of
Its former employes.
        </text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>1</id>
        <rel>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn89055128/1916-10-12/ed-1/seq-5</rel>
        <text>ANOTHER STEP TOWARDS INDUS TRIAL JUSTiGE
declared to be theirs. They set a day to quit work in case the railroad
managers refused them the eight-hour day. Then the railroads in
augurated a strike against the public. They refused to accept freight
tor shipment, especially perishable goods. In many parts of the
country this meant appalling disaster to farmers arid particularly to
fruit growers. It meant great damage to all business—even to the
railroads themselves.
The President stepped in and sough to adjust the trouble and avoid
the disaster about to be thrust upon the country. He was not success
ful. The railway managers were particularly obstinate and refused
to concede the principle of the eight-hour day. At this point the
President put the matter up to Congress for its consideration. Con
gress, disinterested, under law bound to consider ONLY THE PUBLIC
GOOD, was forced to act in the public interest. It was not forced to
act because of any demands upon Congress by the workingmen or by
the railroad managers, but because the public interest demanded im
mediate action.
Congress acted. It passed what is known as the Bight-Hour Day
Bill for men in the employment of railroads in interestate commerce,
engaged in moving trains. EVERY WISCONSIN REPRESENTATIVE
PRESENT VOTED FOR THE BILL WHICH BECAME A LAW AND
AVERTED THE STRIKE.
I believe they did right. I believe in the eight-hour day. It is
claimed that Congress acted "without due consideration." Did it?
The question of the eight-hour day for skilled employees WAS NOT
NEW. Every Congressman who was alive to the issues of the day
must have been fairly familiar with the arguments, pro and con on
the subject of the eight-hour day. I had given this matter considera
tion years ago when I secured the 16-hour limitation for railroad
employees—the best I could get at that time.
At that time I .was met withe THE SAME ARGUMENTS which are
now being made against the eight-hour day. The railroads and some
other large employers are slow to learn, but abundant experience has
shown that for the trades, professions and crafts where skill, cour
age, caution and close attention to business are required the eight
hour day is the maximum for efficiency. Had the railroads accepted
this principle there would have been no trouble.
HOWEVER, RAILROADS GENERALLY YIELD TO NO PRINCI
PLE OF PROGRESS THAT IS NOT FORCED UPON THEM BY LEG
ISLATION.
The Eight-Hour Law for railway trainmen just passed by Congress
has been much misrepresented. During the many months of negotia
tions between the trainmen and the railroad managers, the railroad
companies conducted a tennendous campaign in an effort to influence
public sentiment against the granting of an eight-hour day to their
Their agents worked through chambers of commerce, manu
Ihe dawn of a better day would never brighten the path of
men were it left to the railroad managers.
The railroad employees have been
Theirs is a harardous business.
work
patient and long-suffering.
Their calling takes them away from
their homes at all times of the day and night, in ail kinds of weather.
Their labor is performed under dangerous conditions. Their span of
lift is short and full of grief. They have seen their brothers in other
less hazardous callings secure the eight-hour day without a struggle,
but they have been held to a day of indefinite hours so long as it did
not exceed sixteen, and in cases of unforseen trouble iheir day might
exceed sixteen hours.
men.
facturera' associations and other organizations of business men, induc
ing them to pass resolutions condemning the demand of the trainmen,
and memorializing Congress to enact legislation to empower the Inter
state Commerce Commission to fix the hours and wages of men em
ployèd on railroads engaged in interstate commerce. All of the big
newspapers, and some of the small newspapers, of the country were
flooded with advertisements putting before the public the railroads'
side of this controversy. Millions of dollars must have been expended
1 WONDER THAT THEIR JUST DEMANDS
WERE NOT SOONER MADE.
As long agt^as July, 1913, in an editorial in this magazine, I said:
The wisdom of legislation providing for an eight-hour day. not
only for women but for men as well, is no longer a debatable question.
All practical experience shows that shorter hours
and higher efficiency of employees, the quality of the work and the
character of the output more than offsetting any loss from cutting down
the working hours of the day.
And these millions did not come from the pockets
in this campaign.
of the railroad managers or the railroad owners. They came from the
funds in the treasuries of the railroads. This campaign was conducted
with money that really belonged to the people. The shippers and the
were made—in the last analysis—to finance a publicity
to influence their own judgment upone ONE SIDE of this
means better health
passengers
campaign
great question.
The railroad trainmen had no such resources to enable them to
In other words, shorter hours means
stronger bodies, greater physical efficiency, a higher degree of mental
alertness, keener and more intelligent concentration on the machinery
and material handled by the wage earner, fewer accidents, added time
for home life, rest, recreation, and reading, all making strongly for
moral, mcnatl, and physical improvement.
carry on a publicity campaign to shape public opinion in favor of their
own demands. Nor did they have the additional advantage, enjoyed
by the railroad companies, of placing huge, flamboyant placards upon
the walls of waiting rooms at railway stations setting forth the case
for the railroads before the traveling public.
All this may appears at first glance to be or no importance. But
in the light of what occurred after the strike order had been issued,
and what has happened since Congress took the matter into its hands
—and acted—its bearing upon this controversy will be understood by
every citizen.
This "Eight-Hour Law" has been called a "Force Bill" enacted
under htc demands of organized railroad workmen. This is not true.
The railroad employees demanded the eight-hour day from the rail
"Congress has given men employed by the government or by con
tractors employed on government work, the eight-hour day.
states limit the working day of miners to eight hours in one day.
"The courts have held again and again that rest from labor
Twelve
one
day in seven is 'essential for health, morals, and general welfarë.'
"The courts will ultimately hold that it is vital to the health and
well being of the toller and for that reason vital to the general welfare
that the state should limit the hours of labor for the day as it limits
the days of labor for the week.
"Let the wage earner take heart.
The eight-hour day will come,
and come soon, to ALL of the workers of every state in the nation."
roads, not from Congress. They made no demand whatever upon Con
They said if the railroads did not grant the eight-hour day
This was their right—a right long judicially
gress.
they would quit work.
i
ROBERT M, LA FOLLETTE.
        </text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
</topics>
